<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The merit and honour of the old English clergy asserted by laws and customs patriarchal, mosaical, evangelical, English, ecclesiastick, ethnick, and the demerit of the new clergy discovered / by an author anonymous.</title>
            <author>Author anonymous.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 92 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50647</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1786</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35039</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14956286</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14956286</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102981</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50647)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102981)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1575:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The merit and honour of the old English clergy asserted by laws and customs patriarchal, mosaical, evangelical, English, ecclesiastick, ethnick, and the demerit of the new clergy discovered / by an author anonymous.</title>
                  <author>Author anonymous.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 151 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Royston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102981:1"/>
            <p>THE MERIT AND HONOUR Of the <hi>Old Engliſh</hi> CLERGY. ASSERTED By <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> Patriarchal, Moſaical, Evangelical, Engliſh, Eccleſiaſtick, Ethnick.</p>
            <p>AND The <hi>Demerit</hi> of the New <hi>CLERGY</hi> diſcovered,</p>
            <p>By an Author ANONYMOUS.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Royſton,</hi> Bookſeller to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, at the Angel in <hi>Ivy-Lane,</hi> 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:102981:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102981:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHile the modern Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>Aaron</hi> and the Prieſthood,
<note place="margin">Num. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.2.</note> like their Progenitors, are oft <hi>viri no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis,</hi> men of high name and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown in the Congregation, one of the firſt <hi>Quaeres</hi> of thy thoughts
<pb facs="tcp:102981:3"/>will be (if my Prognoſticks fail not) Why hath this Author no other name, but is <hi>Anonymus</hi> and Apocryphall? Poſsibly it may be from this petty piece of Policy and Prudence, becauſe Authors run the ſame Fate and Deſtiny with their Books, and both are moſt ſought after and admired, when ſuppreſſed and called in. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſuch veils caſt over any the leaſt intellectual Beauty do not make them the leſs amiable or leſs admirable. But to ſpeak more plainly and probably to the Authors ſenſe and intendment, he had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Work ſhould commend the Author, then the Author commend (or diſcommend) the Work; though he really believeth neither the one nor the other very juſtly <hi>commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:102981:3"/>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Let his Name then, Good Reader, be like the Angels to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noah,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Peli,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 13:18.</note> Secret and reſerved. His Clergie-Pride, he feareth, will be thought by the cenſorious Opponents very legible in each Chapter and Line of this Addreſs and Apologie. Is not the Author ſome ſowre and ſupercilious Prieſt? Is not his mind as highly exalted above his people, yea the Gentry, all the Week, as his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the Pulpit on the Sunday? Is hee not a Phariſee, that enlargeth the Phylacteries of Clergie-Honour and Dignity? Iis he not one that loveth the firſt ſeats in Synagogues, and the uppermoſt rooms at Feaſts, and ſo an exquiſite Phariſee in all? In the ſimplicity and ſincerity of a
<pb facs="tcp:102981:4"/>Chriſtian he firſt replieth to thee, that he cordially eſteemeth the whole ſtock of Learning no better then <hi>Zacchaeus</hi> his Sycomore (i. e. <hi>ficus fatua</hi>) a fooliſh bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Fig-tree, fit to be cut down for cumbring the ground, if it keepeth men aloft and in their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, and at greateſt diſtance from their Lord and Maſter, the <hi>meek and lowly</hi> one,
<note place="margin">Mat. 11.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and from aſſociating and complying with the loweſt and meaneſt member of his Church. He wiſheth with equal indifferency each Church-man, and himſelf eſpecially, either like <hi>the Angel attending on the head</hi> (the prime and principal Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) or like <hi>the Angel waiting at the feet</hi> (the leaſt and loweſt member) of his Maſter;
<note place="margin">Joh 20.12</note> or elſe,
<pb facs="tcp:102981:4"/>like <hi>Jacobs</hi> Angel,
<note place="margin">Gen. 28.12.</note> having equal complacence and ſelf-ſatisfaction in his aſcent to the top, or in his deſcent to the loweſt ſtep or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of Church-Order, ſeeing in both ſtations he may have the Angelical Felicity of <hi>alway beholding the face of his Father in Heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.10.</note> He calleth him the moſt Reverend and Venerable Prieſt whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Motto is, <hi>Cor Sacerdotis, Cancellus Chriſti, i. e.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Durant. l.</hi> 1 <hi>ſect.</hi> 21. <hi>Quanta humilitas debet eſſe in Praelato &amp; Clero.</hi>
               </note> the Chancel and the Church-man is <hi>Caput Eccleſiae, i. e.</hi> most high and honourable in the eſtimate of God and the godly-wiſe, even when both are moſt lowly in their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive ſituations and ſtructures, beneath and below any other part of Gods Church, in either ſenſe. The Anonymous Author dareth
<pb facs="tcp:102981:5"/>once adventure to ſay in his own defence, against the common and proverbial reproch of Clergy-Pride, That he hath been ſo little a Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee for <hi>love of firſt ſeats and rooms,</hi> which Chriſt upbraideth <hi>Matth. 23.6.</hi> and <hi>love of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence,</hi> which the Apoſtle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procheth <hi>3 Joh. 9.</hi> that at this preſent day he enjoyeth no Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, no Dignity, no Degree, which was ever obtained <hi>aut prece aut obſequio;</hi> he never yet opened his lips to any Maſter of the Feaſts, to <hi>bid him ſit up higher;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 14.10.</note> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting Preferment juſt as the godly Prieſts ſhadow; both of greateſt dimenſions commonly in the declination of their age, and both by their preſence or abſence ſcarce adding one Cubit either to
<pb facs="tcp:102981:5"/>his own merit and just value, or to his own perſonal content and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. He hath ever taken preferment as Chriſt would have him <hi>take up his Croſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.24. Yet many primitive Saints <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily</hi> after Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loved it then an Epiſcopal Throne: <hi>Theodor. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 38.</note> not by running after it, but by not run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from it, or declining it when offered and impoſed by the ſupreme Hand of Providence. In ſhort, each honeſt and truly venerable Prieſt would gladly vote a new Edition and Impreſsion (upon the Table of his Heart) of the old Church-Canons <hi>contra Ambitum.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith Saint <hi>Baſil, Conſtit. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſt. c. 9. To be ambitious of the Order of Prieſthood, and of Preeminence in that Order, is the Devils diſeaſe and diſtemper,</hi> rather becoming
<pb facs="tcp:102981:6"/>a ſon of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> that cried, <hi>Aſcendam, &amp; ero ſimilis Altiſsimo,</hi> Iſa. <hi>14.14. I will aſcend, and be like the higheſt</hi> in the Clerical Order, then a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciple of Chriſt, who ſhould be content to ſit in any, though the loweſt, <hi>Claſsis.</hi> Again, in the ſame ſtyle of Antiquity, <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè ambiendus qui minimè ambitioſus: non ſtudet ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere Sacerdotium, ſed mereri,</hi> as <hi>Sidonius Apollina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> reporteth of <hi>Simplicius</hi> a Catholick Biſhop; <hi>He did moſt merit to be ſought after that was leaſt a ſeeker, and ſtudied rather to merit a Dignity then to obtain and enjoy it.</hi> Even in Offices of eivil and ſecular concernment, <hi>qui ad civile mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus
<pb facs="tcp:102981:6"/>ambitioſe perveniſſet, puniendus.</hi> So the Codex of <hi>Theodoſius, l. 1. Defenſ. Civit.</hi> He awardeth penalty rather then dignity to any ſelf-ſeeking Officer. In Spiritual and Eccleſiaſtick pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, <hi>indignus Sacerdotio &amp; honoribus, qui non invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus illos acciperet:</hi> He deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riteth <hi>ipſo facto</hi> any Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal dignity, that receiveth it not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h ſome <hi>nolleity</hi> &amp; reluctancie. He must be ſo far from ambition,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cod. de E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſc. &amp; Clero, l.</hi> 30.</note> 
               <hi>ut quaeratur cogendus, roga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus recedat, ſola illi ſuffragetur non recuſandi neceſsitas:</hi> He muſt be firſt a modeſt Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, before he is made Reſident <hi>in cathedra,</hi> by no other motive but by the neceſsity of his obedience. Some young Divines, like <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchs</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:102981:7"/>young Philoſophers, are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, like thoſe Sparrows that ſtill fly and mount up to the top of the houſe; whereas they ſhould rather, like <hi>Davids</hi> Sparrows, be content with any room or place near Gods Altar and in his Sanctuary. And what Chriſtian knoweth not that the Devil was once on the pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of the Temple, whereas Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, <hi>the high one of God,</hi> (as his name is by interpretation) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> placed <hi>in puteo,</hi> in a low place of mire and dirt; and yet was ſtill <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>like his name,</hi> in that very ſtation, or dejection rather?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> I know again, that this Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymous Author, or any Advocate of Clergie-Revenues and Dignity, will be impeached by the common <hi>Genius</hi> of this Age, as guilty either
<pb facs="tcp:102981:7"/>of ſome diſcontent and diſſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with his own eſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or elſe of the Idolatry of <hi>Mammon,</hi> that is, Covetouſneſs. Can the Author make any Bar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst that common Plea of Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adverſaries? In the aforeſaid ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity and ſincerity of a Christian Priest he can and will ſay, (if his own heart be not his own <hi>Jacob,</hi> that is, his own <hi>Supplanter</hi> and <hi>Deceiver,</hi> according to that He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew Elegancy of Scripture, <hi>Jer. 17.9.)</hi> and he doth ſay,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>W. C.</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nton.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in the words of a late godly Prelate, who loſt the beſt Biſhoprick in all En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, a few dayes before his death,</hi> I thank God, I never knew that night in which I loſt one quarter of an hours reſt or ſleep for all my own perſonal
<pb facs="tcp:102981:8"/>
               <hi>loſſes and deprivations.</hi> Yea, the Author is ſo far from all paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xyſmes of diſcontent in either ſtate, that he hath imbibed this principle or <hi>dogma</hi> with the very milk of his Mother the Univerſity, <hi>That there is very ſmall or no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, excepting the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of poverty and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Teeth, 'twixt high or low eſtates of any perſon, Temporal or Eccleſiaſtick.</hi> His ground is unmoveable, and his reaſon invincible from Gods own mouth. When God himſelf was Lord Almoner to his own people, of both Orders, Lay and Clergy, and gave them a daily allowance of Manna from his own immediate hand, it is expreſly ſaid, <hi>He that gathered much, had nothing
<pb facs="tcp:102981:8"/>over; and he that gathered little, had no lack,</hi> Exod. <hi>16.18. Nothing over,</hi> and <hi>no lack,</hi> are plainly and literally terms equivalent and equipollent, even Levelling terms, And thus far the Author is a profeſſed Leveller in his practick judgement, paſt and preſent; a very <hi>Lazarus,</hi> that <hi>gathereth little;</hi> yet by Some other benediction, of Autarkie and Self-ſufficiency, a very <hi>Dives,</hi> He <hi>hath no lack.</hi> And if by the rule of Reaſon, <hi>Perfectum eſt cui nihil deeſt,</hi> then even a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtered perſon hath and enjoyeth a perfect happineſs of eſtate. This is no more then another Greek Copy (in another mount, that of <hi>Sion,</hi> under the Goſpel, as well as that of <hi>Sinai</hi> under the Law) rendreth
<pb facs="tcp:102981:9"/>thus, <hi>When without purſe, and ſcrip, and ſhoes, lacked ye any thing?</hi> Luk. <hi>22.35.</hi> It is the gallant and daring <hi>Quaere</hi> of our Great Rabbi to his own Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples. Though then the Anony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Author might probably and juſtly ſay, for a double Apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of years,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 7.131,</note> with <hi>Luther, Ego pro annuo ſtipendio tantùm novem antiquas ſexagenas habeo: praeter has nè obolus quidem aut mihi, aut fratri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus è civitate accedit,</hi> that is, onely ſixty pounds for his annual ſtipend; yet he then was, and he hopeth ever ſhall be, ſo far from a querulous temper, that when <hi>he gathered much, he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing over;</hi> and when <hi>little, he had no lack</hi> of ſufficient content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:102981:9"/>and ſatisfaction. I would now heartily wiſh and pray for my Brethren, that there were no one ſon of <hi>Eli</hi> the Prieſt among them, not one that may make <hi>the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of the Lord ſtink,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 1.17.</note> even under the Goſpel, by their foul and ſordid humour of Covetouſneſs in any State.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.3</note> 
               <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> ſhould <hi>not be once named among them, as becometh Saints;</hi> much leſs ſhould it be acted and practiced amongst them, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh Prieſts eſpecially. But it is much to be bewailed, that even ſome Spiritual perſons are ſo much fleſh and blood, and ſo obnoxious to that foul and mechanick office of <hi>lading themſelves with thick clay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. 2.6.</note> that they alſo cry out with profane <hi>Eſau, Da mihi de ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo,
<pb facs="tcp:102981:10"/>rufo illo,</hi> Gen. <hi>25.30. Give me that red, that red Clay;</hi> whereas even the chief Apoſtle was neither aſhamed nor diſcontented to ſay, <hi>Silver and Gold have I none,</hi> Act. <hi>3.6.</hi> Both Lay and Clergy-order may and muſt know, that it is with the Revenues of Priests as with the Phylacteries of the Phariſees. God himſelf allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yea injoyned, <hi>Exod. 13.16. Deut. 6.8.</hi> (they were <hi>jure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino)</hi> the uſe of theſe Phylacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: yet when there was an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement and ampliation of them, though they were <hi>conſervatoria pietatis</hi> (as their name import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) it was condemned by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Souls in the very Phariſees, <hi>Matth. 23.5.</hi> Thus, even juſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with Church-Revenues.
<pb facs="tcp:102981:10"/>God doth not only allow and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, but alſo enjoyneth a large and liberal income to Church-men; eſpecially in times of affluence, peace and plenty in the Chriſtian State: And theſe Revenues alſo are <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatoria pietatis,</hi> great conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatories and encouragements of Piety and Religion. But when there is an enlargement or a dilata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them to Pride, Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Luxury, or Lazineſs, ſuch Grandees are but Phariſaical Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies, and will be ſadly obnoxious to the ſevere cenſure and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great Biſhop of Soules at his laſt and Oecumenical Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And I, and each true Son of the Church, do heartily wiſh, that our <hi>Vicarius Dei in ſuo Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> (as Pope <hi>Eleutherius</hi> entitleth
<pb facs="tcp:102981:11"/>the King) and all his Senate or Councel would give what ſevere Orders or Acts they pleaſe againſt any ſuch Spiritual Dilapidations which the Luxury, Covetouſneſs, or Lazineſs of any of that Order may bring upon the Church of God. For though I ſhall ever honour the linen Ephod upon any Goſpel-Prieſt; yet when I ſee a carking covetous Prieſt, I cannot but point with the finger, as the Iſraelites of old,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Weemſe</hi> on Prieſts veſtments.</note> and ſay, <hi>Behold the Prieſt with the rough and rugged Garment, i. e.</hi> one of a rugged and rigid temper, or of a ſecular and covetous diſpoſition. And yet I doubt not but the <hi>holy and harmleſs Prieſt</hi> and great <hi>Biſhop of Souls</hi> oft permitteth and vouchſafeth room in his own
<note place="margin">Zech. 13 4</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:102981:11"/>Society and Church to ſuch or ſuch a <hi>Judas,</hi> that carrieth the bag, and yet betrayeth his Maſter and his Spouſe the Church. That I may conclude this Subject; I have ſometimes ſmiled at the Romiſh either Wit or ſeeming Piety, that giveth this Reaſon for the <hi>Raſura capitis,</hi> the ſhaving of Prieſts heads in their Church; That there may be <hi>Nil medium inter Coelum &amp; Sacerdotem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Durant. de ritibus.</note> not ſo much as an hair intervenient 'twixt Heaven and their Priests: But I heartily wiſh that both our heads and hearts would prove us to be ſuch true Nazarites to God, as not to grieve to be ſhaved when we are ſequeſtred and deprived by the ſharpneſs of a malicious age; and to be ſo far from <hi>lading our
<pb facs="tcp:102981:12"/>ſelves with thick Clay,</hi> as to <hi>lay up</hi> little or no <hi>treaſure upon earth,</hi> but <hi>a good foundation againſt the time to come, 1</hi> Tim. <hi>6.19. ut nihil ſit me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium inter Coelum &amp; Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> A third Article or impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Common Pleas of this Age will be, Is not this Author and Advocate of the Clergy guilty of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, malice, or malignity to the Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? It is anſwered; As that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and indulgent Husband once ſaid, <hi>Se cum uxore nunquam in gratiam rediiſſe,</hi> That he was never (for forty or fifty years) once reconciled to his Wife; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no jarre or domeſtick quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel had been ever betwixt them in the revolution of ſo many years:
<pb facs="tcp:102981:12"/>even ſo may this Author profeſs, That he was never once reconciled with any one Pariſhioner, nor ſo much as once convented (except before Committees for Plundring Miniſters) nor did ever convent any one ſingle perſon (except one, who was ſo exorbitant and irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar as he never paid King, or Church, or Poor almoſt, without a <hi>Diſtringas)</hi> before any Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Eccleſiaſtick or Civil. The Author much admireth that bond and obligation of the three Britan Kings upon all their Lay-Subjects, to wit, That all ſhould take the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury of a Prieſt as an injury done to all; and, That the best and noble perſons ſhould be <hi>loco cognato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; patroni,</hi> ſuch Patrons of the Clergie as if ſome conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb facs="tcp:102981:13"/>in nature were betwixt both Orders. Thus <hi>Kenneth</hi> the <hi>I.</hi> King of the Scots, <hi>Anno 840.</hi> the Learned King <hi>Alfred, Anno 905.</hi> and King <hi>Edgar, Can. 5.</hi> How Chriſtian, how gratious, how gallant would ſuch Lay-Charity be to the Order of the Church! But the Author applieth one Canon, more proper and pertinent to his own Order, even unto his own heart and ſoul, and unto the ſouls of all the Clergie of the Church, as truly adoring that old Engliſh word;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhev. Concil ſub. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uth rio Archiep. apud Spel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man p.</hi> 25<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ut praedicator pacis &amp; charitatis nullum invidiae aut odii fomitem adverſus Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, nè ad momentum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, ſuſciperet:</hi> That is, in Engliſh Tranſlation, and practice too, I hope, <hi>That no Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher
<pb facs="tcp:102981:13"/>of peace and charity ſhould entertain the fewel &amp;</hi> fomes <hi>of envy and malignity towards any of the Laity, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for one ſingle moment or minute.</hi> Laſtly, he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureth himſelf, and exhorteth all of Sacred Order to a treble Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Ambition or Emulation, even in Apoſtolicall Language: <hi>1.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>To be ambitiouſly emulous of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Love and Peace,</hi> Rom. <hi>15.20. 2.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>To be Leaders and Captains in giving honour to others,</hi> not in ſnatching to themſelves, <hi>Rom. 12.10. 3.</hi> Laſtly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>1</hi> Theſ. <hi>4.11. To be ambitiouſly</hi> inquiſitive of the true Chriſtian and Clerical
<pb facs="tcp:102981:14"/>mode <hi>of being quiet</hi> and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and even induſtrious Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in that Chriſtian Art of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and love. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> There is yet behind one Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle and Impeachment in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pleas of the Age againſt the Clergie, concerning the idleneſs and lazineſs of ſome of the Church-order. I muſt aſſert and confeſs it to both Orders, that the only defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of a Church-man, or Man of God, which I find in any page or line of either Teſtament, is moſt probably that of S. <hi>Paul, 2</hi> Tim. <hi>3.17.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The Miniſter is <hi>the Man of God well joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and compoſed</hi> (or <hi>exactly articulated) to every good work:</hi> His ſoul not diſlocated, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynted,
<pb facs="tcp:102981:14"/>or lame and defective in the paths of Piety to God, or Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to his Brother. As for Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers in Gods Harveſt, I know not any <hi>Animal,</hi> that liveth, moveth, and hath a being upon Gods earth, that is more deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or deteſtable then a Spiritual Shepherd that zelouſly mindeth the Fleece or Fat of his Flock, ſtudieth no Book ſo much as his Eaſter-Book, and (in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> words) <hi>buildeth</hi> with <hi>Gold</hi> or <hi>Silver</hi> for himſelf,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.12.</note> and affordeth only <hi>Hay</hi> or <hi>Stubble</hi> to his flock. This is not to <hi>give attendance to reading, to exhortation, to doctrine;</hi> this is not to <hi>give himſelf wholly to them,</hi> and <hi>continue in them, 1</hi> Tim. <hi>4.13, 15, 16.</hi> This is not to <hi>endure
<pb facs="tcp:102981:15"/>hardneſs as a good ſouldier of Jeſus Chriſt, 2</hi> Tim. <hi>2.3.</hi> There is indeed a <hi>Militia imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> as the Law in <hi>Duarenus</hi> calleth it, when ſecular Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers do no duty, lie ſtill in warm quarters and ſecure Garriſons, and yet receive pay: But in the Sacred <hi>Militia,</hi> he that is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>2</hi> Tim. <hi>2.3.</hi> and yet <hi>miles imaginarius</hi> alſo, hath a baſe and diſhonourable Chivalry:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Super Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, p.</hi> 837.</note> call him <hi>ſalem infatuatum,</hi> ſaith honeſt <hi>Gerſon, ſalt that hath loſt its ſavour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.13.</note> fit onely <hi>for the dunghill, and to be troden under foot by men,</hi> and by Angels alſo. He that lieth ſtill and warm <hi>in die Solis,</hi> on many, many Chriſtian <hi>Sundayes,</hi> and doth not,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 19.5.</note> as the Sun, <hi>rejoyce as
<pb facs="tcp:102981:15"/>a Giant to run the courſe</hi> of his Function, doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the bleſsing of the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, <hi>Jer. 31.14. I will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate the Soule of the Prieſts with Fatneſs.</hi> But that curſe rather is his portion, <hi>His right eye ſhall be utterly darkned,</hi> Zech. <hi>11.17.</hi> and <hi>his Sun ſhall go down</hi> at noon-day, <hi>Mich. 3.6.</hi> and ſo he ſhall be a very <hi>Sodomite,</hi> groping at the Door both of the Church Militant and Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant alſo.
<note place="margin">Gen. 19.11.</note> The Hebrew Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb of each Iſraelite was, <hi>Bleſſed is he that duſteth himſelfe in the duſt of the Temple.</hi> And whereas the Miniſter carrieth <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Duſt</hi> in his name <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb facs="tcp:102981:16"/>
               <hi>Bleſſed is he that duſteth himſelfe in the Duſt of the Pulpit.</hi> And for Honour and Aſsiduity of that Labour in that Duſt ye have the united Votes and Suffrages of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councills, <hi>Concil. Tolet. 2. Can. 4. Tom. 4. pag. 800. Conſtantinop. 2. Can. 19. Tom. 5. pag. 328. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relian. Can. 33. pag. 713. Trident. Seſſ. 24. Can. 4.</hi> In fine or Concluſion, whereas the Baſes of the Temple had Oxen pourtrayed on them, and Lions, and Cherubim, this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonymous Advocate of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie wiſheth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>H. Pintus</hi> in Iſa. 31.</note> even with a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Author, that each Engliſh Church-man were ſuch a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis of the Temple,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15:</note> 
               <hi>a pillar and
<pb facs="tcp:102981:16"/>ground of Truth,</hi> to his utmoſt poſsibility; to wit, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of the Oxen, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant labour and induſtry; of the Lion, for courage againſt the moſt daring Offenders; and of the Cherub, <hi>Ob ſcientiae plenitudinem,</hi> for fulneſs of illumination and inſtruction. And ſuch a Church-man as this doth juſtly merit the complicated, decompounded and ſuperabun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant honour which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> enjoyneth, <hi>1 Theſſ. 5.13.</hi> and which is the whole intendment and deſign of this Anonymous Author: who in an holy and humble imitation of him who wrote himſelfe, not <hi>by the Grace of God,</hi> nor <hi>by the
<pb facs="tcp:102981:17"/>Providence of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Durandi Rationale, in Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m.</note> but <hi>ſolâ Dei patientiâ Epiſcopus,</hi> doth juſtly write himſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By the meer Patience of God, His Presbyter,</hi> And <hi>Your moſt humble Servant,</hi>A. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102981:17"/>
            <head>The <hi>Merit</hi> of the Old, <hi>AND Demerit</hi> of the New <hi>ENGLISH CLERGY demonſtrated.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION I. <hi>An Introduction concerning the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern</hi> Zamzummims <hi>and miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Agitators againſt the Clergy.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">To the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentry.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Moſt generous and courteous Sirs,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here have been of late ſome <hi>Zamzum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mims</hi> and ſons of <hi>Anak</hi> amongſt you, though not of you. Theſe (as their Name is by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation) have been <hi>Turpia &amp; prava cogitantes ac molientes, i. e.</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:102981:18"/>Great Inventors and Maſters of Miſchief. And the gemination of the word,
<note place="margin">Deut. 2.20, 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Zamzummim,</hi> notes in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> dialect, High and mighty ones for ſtrength of Body and Mind to do miſchief, or hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid machinations. Theſe have looked upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (of the firſt and beſt Edition in this Century) as upon ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inconſiderable and deſpicable <hi>Graſhoppers</hi> of the Earth.
<note place="margin">Num. 13.33.</note> And while the Sacred Scripture calls them indeed <hi>Earthen Veſſels,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.7.</note> they have made them all in their new account no better then <hi>Terrae filii, i. e.</hi> Sons of the Earth, men of baſe and vile Allay in reſpect of their Generous Order. And yet by the diſpenſation of Divine Providence, both theſe ſons of <hi>Anak</hi> (to complete the Parallel) have been themſelves odious and deſpicable in the eyes of the King of Kings and Lord of Lords, and that menace and commination is almoſt verified,
<note place="margin">Pſa. 73.20</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt make
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102981:18"/>their Image to vaniſh out of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> Theſe men have had a gallant <hi>Levelling</hi> Project in reference to the <hi>Church,</hi> while Self-intereſt hath forbade any ſuch deſign in relation to the <hi>State</hi> and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth.</p>
               <p>It's very true, that the <hi>God of Order</hi> and <hi>Father of Lights</hi> hath made and conſtituted a double <hi>Aequinoctial</hi> in the compaſs of the Year, the one <hi>Vernal,</hi> the other <hi>Autumnal,</hi> in which the brighteſt Day cannot brag of a Minutes length beyond the ſouleſt and darkeſt Night. But theſe ſons of Diſorder and Confuſion have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and often voted and deſigned a third and new <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctial</hi> in the <hi>Church;</hi> in which the <hi>Lights</hi> of the firſt, ſecond and third Magnitude muſt be equalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with the moſt obſcure, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and illiterate Teachers. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would they have any regret or averſion, if all ſuch <hi>Lights</hi> had been whelmed <hi>ſub modio,</hi> under a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102981:19"/>Buſhel, or (like <hi>Achans</hi> accurſed thing) buried under ground, and not one of them ſet up in a <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtick,</hi> eſpecially if it be a <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> one, a place of value and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence.</p>
               <p>It ſeems the ſond Fancy of ſome ſons of falſe Light in old <hi>Tertullians</hi> dayes, by a <hi>Platonick</hi> Revolution, hath lighted upon our modern Age:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertul. de Monoga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, c.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Quum extollimur &amp; inflamur adverſus Clerum, tunc Unum Omnes ſumus, tunc Omnes Sacerdotes, &amp;c. i.e.</hi> When we are extolled and ſwollen big with a Tympany of ſpiritual pride, then we are all One, and all Prieſts; and that not without a Sacred Text to juſtifie it (a very <hi>Jus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinum</hi> for contempt of Miniſtery) <hi>Sacerdotes nos Deo &amp; Patri fecit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apo. 5.10.</note> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> We are all Kings, all Prieſts to God.
<note place="margin">Jude 11.</note> Juſt all <hi>Corahs</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany (for <hi>the gainſaying of Corah</hi> is a ſin under the Goſpel) All the Congregation are <hi>Sancti,</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y one of them Saints and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102981:19"/>as holy Orders can make them.</p>
               <p>Theſe grand Agitators and Pragmaticks in Church-affairs have poſſibly another fair (or foul) Precedent from ſome of their modern Progenitors, even in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes.
<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Henry Spelm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns</hi> Preface to his <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils.</hi>
                  </note> The Plot was this: That while in our Royal <hi>Engliſh</hi> Armes there is the <hi>Croſs</hi> and the <hi>Lily</hi> in a fair conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, their Envious eyes would have wholly raſed out the <hi>Croſs</hi> (the Embleme of the Church) that ſo the <hi>Lily</hi> (the Embleme and Cogniſance of the State) might ſingly and ſolely flouriſh, exceeding <hi>Salomon</hi> in all his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>If theſe men had gone one ſtep further in their <hi>furious Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al,</hi> &amp; <hi>unâ &amp; eâdem liturâ,</hi> by one and the ſame motion had blotted out and expung'd the <hi>Croſs</hi> from their own Foreheads, had they not made themſelves and the whole State very Gallant and Triumphant
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102981:20"/>Chriſtians? And whereas it was once the pious Vote of a King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and one learned in all the Wiſdom of the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and the man of Viſions and Miracles beyond all others,
<note place="margin">Num. 11.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Would to God all the Lords people were Prophets;</hi> that Vote would have been by theſe wholly inverted, or perverted, <hi>Would to God all the Lords Prophets were no other then one of the people:</hi> and ſo the <hi>Croſs</hi> it ſelf (the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of the Church and Church-men) wholly have been crucified to all intents and purpoſes.</p>
               <p>I am now aſhamed and bluſh (Gentle and Honoured Sirs) that I ſhould tell you ſuch true ſtories of our own <hi>Zamzummims,</hi> ſons of falſe Light and Fanatick Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, before whom the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or Carkaſs, of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church bled afreſh, at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of ſuch Monſters of men. God grant there be no Spawn or Iſſue left of ſuch Levelling <hi>Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites,</hi> that ſtill cry, <hi>Down with it,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102981:20"/>down with it even to the ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Authors grand Deſign by theſe ſmall Papers is, to make our own <hi>Engliſh</hi> Statute more authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick and unrepealable in all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> generous and Chriſtian hearts,
<note place="margin">8 <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>z. cap.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. in Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble.</note> namely that of 8 <hi>Elizabeth cap.</hi> 1. That <hi>the Clergy is a High State, one of the greateſt States of the Realm.</hi> And this ſhall be aſſerted againſt all our new <hi>Edomites,</hi> 1. <hi>Jure An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-Anglican<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> by the old <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> account; 2. <hi>Jure Naturae &amp; Patriarchali,</hi> by the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Patriarchs before the Law; 3. <hi>Jure Moſaico &amp; Iſraeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico,</hi> under the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> 4. <hi>Jure Evangelico,</hi> by the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical account; 5. <hi>Jure Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtico,</hi> by Primitive Eccleſiaſtick account; 6. <hi>Jure Ethnico,</hi> even by the account of Heathens them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>But before all or any of thoſe, I am conſtrained from the urgency of the preſent Poſture of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Affairs, to give my Reader a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102981:21"/>double Eſſay or Exercitation: One touching the Merit and juſt Value of the true Old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy; The other touching the Demerits and depreciating the New <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy, and of all <hi>Sectaries,</hi> of what diviſion, ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, and of what denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſoever. Though poſſibly (upon Second thoughts) the grand Defects and huge and groſs Enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of all ſuch Factious ſpirits, like the <hi>Faces</hi> or Dregs, are moſt fit and proper for the Bottom and Sediment of this Diſcourſe; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which I ſhall defer them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>Of the grand Merit of the Old</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Clergy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LEt not, I pray (Generous and Courteous Sirs) this one word ſeem the effect of Clergy-Pride, if we dare venture to tell you, That there are no leſs then eight
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102981:21"/>or nine ſignal and eminent Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Favours which the Great and Catholick Biſhop of Souls hath vouchſafed to our Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick Order; equal to which the Divine Benediction hath hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deign'd to any Age or any Kingdom beſides.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Speeds</hi> Hiſt. l. 9. c. 19. pag. 9 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</note> The Union of the Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> was effected by the Counſels of Biſhop <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</hi> A rare Accommodation and Expedient for the joynt &amp; united welfare of the Church and State.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Idem, c.</hi> 20. pag 989.</note> The Union of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> was wrought by the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Biſhop <hi>Foxe.</hi> That great Wall of Partition was beaten down by a bleſſed Epiſcopal Hand.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Converſion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from Paganiſm was by Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> Epiſtle to <hi>Epiſc. aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted.</hi>
                  </note> The Reformation was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun and promoted by Biſhops. Theſe were thoſe <hi>Aarons,</hi> whoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102981:22"/>hands lift up did defeat all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> and gave Benediction to all true <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> So that we may borrow (without juſt Envy) the words of K. <hi>Alured</hi> to <hi>Walfigeus</hi> the Biſhop, <hi>Felicia tunc tempora fuerunt inter omnes Anglia populos, &amp;c. i. e. England</hi> was oft the Fortunate Iſland. His Reaſon is, <hi>Sapientes extiterunt in Anglica gente de Spirituali gradu, &amp;c.</hi> Becauſe thoſe of Spiritual Order were Learned, Wiſe and Godly.</p>
               <p>Let this make a fifth ſignal Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſon even in a modern Age: That as in <hi>England</hi> a judicious and authentick Antiquary hath fixed this Aſteriſm upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kings,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Spolman</hi> Concil. Praef.</note> 
                  <hi>Plures pii Reges in Anglia quàm in ulla alia Provincia, quantumcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> populoſa, i. e.</hi> More pious Kings have been in little <hi>England,</hi> then in any other Province, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo populous or numerous: ſo the ſame Divine Benediction hath beſtowed a ſingularity and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102981:22"/>of Favour and Honour upon the Body of this Clergy,
<q>That there have been more Learned men in <hi>England</hi> then are to be found among all the Miniſters of the Religion in <hi>France, Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Germany, Poland, Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, Scotland,</hi> and all <hi>Europe</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides.</q> Thus <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxford</hi> anſwer to the <hi>Puritan</hi> Petition ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to K. <hi>James Anno</hi> 1603. <hi>pag.</hi> 31. And can it once be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined by him that hath Charity as a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, that ſuch a numerous company of ſuch Learned, Grave and Judicious Clerks ſhould prefer a Libel to ſuch a Learned and Judicious Prince as he was?</p>
               <p>Adde yet a ſixth ſignal Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, That the late moſt Odious (<hi>i. e.</hi> Dignified) Clergy, as Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Deans and Prebends, have been <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (in the ſingular and new-coined Greek of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel) <hi>highly favoured</hi> and honoured above others. For though their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102981:23"/>Number exceeds not above 4. or 500.
<note place="margin">Cambden.</note> perſons, yet they have been more Able and Athletick and Publick Champions of Proteſtant religion againſt Popery, then above 9284. Parochial Miniſters. In this I dare appeal to all Learned Gentry or Clergy of what Party or Perſuaſion ſoever. Theſe, like <hi>Gedeons</hi> 300. Souldiers, have done the Duty and Service of many thouſands, though their Reward hath been of late, to be diſcarded and disbanded by the men of the new <hi>Militia,</hi> or <hi>Malitia</hi> rather.</p>
               <p>If all theſe Six ſignal Honours adde nothing to the Merit and Price of that <hi>Engliſh</hi> Order, let them give them all an Oſtraciſm for an Honorary,
<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> and write upon them, <hi>Nemo inter vos excellat;</hi> an <hi>Athenian</hi> baniſhment for ten years, for being too much <hi>Athenian</hi> or Learned.</p>
               <p>That I may yet adde <hi>ad cumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> and make up a very <hi>Galeed, i. e.</hi> an heap, of Witneſſes, take a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102981:23"/>ſeventh ſignal Honour and Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, which is the greater be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it comes out of the mouth of an Enemy. Even one of the grand <hi>Rabbies</hi> and Patriarchs of the Modern Age gives them a fair voluntary Atteſtation and ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Confeſſion. His own words are theſe enſuing.
<q>If we had been at Gods elbow (ſuch his own dialect and language) when he bounded out the Nations, and appointed out Times and Seaſons that men ſhould live in, we ſhould not have known in what Place or Nation we ſhould have choſen to have lived, in reſpect of the enjoyment of the Goſpel, rather then in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</q> So <hi>Thom as Goodwin</hi> in his <hi>Grand Intereſt of State, Febr.</hi> 25. 1645. This <hi>Ex ore tuo</hi> then was ſpoken above 20. years before that date, as himſelf witneſſes; When the Epiſcopal Order and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liturgy were in their very <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and altitude, their very Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Luſtre.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102981:24"/>
               <p>Another <hi>Rabbi</hi> of the ſame Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity gives a fair Conceſſion extorted only by the virtue and force of Truth, and that with no ſmall Paſſion and Indignation.
<q>O how does the Carriage of theſe men in ſome degree juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Harſhneſs, Sourneſs, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering and Cruelty of ſome of the Prelates? There is occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion given to think they were not ſuch vile men as heretofore we thought they were.</q> So <hi>Jer. Burroughs, Irenici</hi> pag. 216. <hi>Anno</hi> 1646.
<note place="margin">John 11.51.</note> 
                  <hi>This,</hi> ſure, <hi>he ſpake not of himſelf, but as being a High Prieſt</hi> (and true Prophet) <hi>for that</hi> ſame <hi>year.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the mouth of two or three Witneſſes will not eſtabliſh this word, hear the grand and united Authors of the late <hi>deformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</hi>
                  <q>That inſtead of true Piety and Power of Godlineſs, they had opened the very floud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates to all Impiety and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs; and that after they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102981:24"/>had removed the Prelatical yoke from their ſhoulders (which they had tied on with their own Hands and Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</q> and were now <hi>Viri Belial, without yoke</hi>) by their Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<q>endeavours, there was a rueful, deplorable and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med face of the affairs of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: That inſtead of <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> they might ſay with Sighs, what their Enemies ſaid in Scorn, they had a <hi>Deformation</hi> in Religion, and ſwarming with noiſom Errours, Hereſies and Blaſphemies, Schiſm, Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Diviſions and Subdiviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</q> Thus, thus the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>J. C.</hi> ſubſcribed by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Province of <hi>London, pag.</hi> 26, 29, 30, 31.</p>
               <p>You may eaſily judge (Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Gentlemen) what kind of Builders they were, without any Edification; though their fingers do very much itch (if their Wits were as good as their Wills) to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102981:25"/>rear up a ſecond <hi>Babel.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Let the <hi>Reverend Clergy</hi> then (yet further) <hi>Ride on proſperouſly,</hi> and <hi>good luck have they with their</hi> ſignal <hi>Honour</hi> in the eighth place, from the indifferent, impartial Tranſmarine Teſtimony. <hi>Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsima Anglia, Ocellus ille Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Peculium Chriſti ſingulare, Spei melioris vexillum, ſplendida Domini caulae. — Horrore toti con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutimur ad verſam hanc pulcherri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam Eccleſiae inter vos faciem.— hactenus in terris &amp; Eccleſiae Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro eminuere. i. e.</hi> The moſt Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid and Illuſtrious Church, the right Eye of the Churches, Chriſts own grand Peculiar, the very En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and Banner of all good Hope, the moſt ſplendid Sheepfold of <hi>the great Shepherd and Biſhop of Souls,</hi> the moſt fair and eminent Candleſtick on the Theatre. Thus, even thus, the very <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va</hi>-men and their Learned <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odate, ad Conventum Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Londini.</hi> Sound Doctrine
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102981:25"/>for the late Aſſembly-men.</p>
               <p>Again, is it not very Rare and Admirable, that with the <hi>Geneva</hi>-men, another Tranſmarine Author, a <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadour (Monſieur <hi>Rogne</hi>) ſings an almoſt <hi>Antiphonon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conference</hi> at <hi>Hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-Court,</hi> ſecond day, p. 38.</note> giving out at Court and at <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> upon the view of our Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Church-Service,
<q>That if the Reformed Churches in <hi>France</hi> had kept the ſame Orders a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them which we obſerv'd, he was aſſured that there would have been many Thouſands of Proteſtants more there then now there are.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now as thoſe eminent Tranſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine Perſons were at leaſt ſeeming Fautors and Fomenters of our old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church; ſo others (of a more gallant Equipage then any Novel Teachers) were no friends to the profane violaters of Sacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or Revenues of the Church. <hi>Luther</hi> for <hi>Germany</hi> calls
<q>Bona Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pae (<hi>i. e.</hi> as they are miſcalled,</q> Landes of Biſhops, Deanes and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102981:26"/>
                  <q>Chapters) the Churches juſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luther</hi> on Gal. 6.6.</note> not to be deprived by the Laiety upon Scruples of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, becauſe Popiſh, &amp;c. and (ſayes he) the Devils own high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to deſtroy Religion is either by Errours of Hereticks, or elſe by depriving or defrauding Gods Miniſters: and this is the Devils Maſter-plot.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This is a <hi>German</hi> Witneſs ſerving indifferently for our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon. <hi>Calvin</hi> for <hi>France</hi> does not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend our <hi>Engliſh Zamzummims,</hi> who complains,
<q>That the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Chriſt and the Patrimony of the Church are not employed to the Sacred Honour of the Clergy, is my grief; and all good men lament this caſe with me.</q> So <hi>Calvin de Neceſsit. Reform.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>Knox</hi> for <hi>Scotland</hi> gave this death-bed Doctrine againſt our <hi>Engliſh</hi> falſe Teachers:
<q>Brethren (ſaith he) we have fought againſt Hereticks, and God hath bleſſed us: we muſt now have a ſtrong
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102981:26"/>fight againſt the Sacrilegious.</q> And accordingly at <hi>St. Andrews An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1582. there was a general Faſt throughout the Realm for appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Gods wrath for the ſin of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege.</p>
               <p>Let our Novel Teachers in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> either defie this Quaternion of Goſpel-Souldiers, <hi>Diodati</hi> for <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva, Luther</hi> for <hi>Germany, Calvin</hi> for <hi>France, Knox</hi> for <hi>Scotland;</hi> or elſe down on their knees, and aske Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and Bleſſing from their old Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church, or their Fathers the Biſhops of that Church.</p>
               <p>In the ninth and laſt place, the Honour of the old Clergy might be demonſtrated and made viſible and conſpicuous from the <hi>Antitheſis</hi> of all Novel Teachers. <hi>Oppoſita juxta ſe poſita magis eluceſcunt.</hi> Their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience and Rebellion, their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilege, their Perjury, their Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating of Creed, ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, their Oppreſſion and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of Brethren (againſt the Laws
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102981:27"/>of their own Maſters) their Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, Temporizing, and Symboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing with Papiſts (in more then ten or twelve particulars;) theſe, theſe are the Lees and Dregs which (as before was ſaid) ſhall be reſerved for the very Bottom and Sediment of our whole Diſcourſe; if our good <hi>Constantines Mantle, i. e.</hi> our King <hi>Charles</hi> his Act of Oblivion, do not palliate, even wholly cover and hide them; or ſuch foul matters will not make my Papers rather ſink then bear them. However, here I give breath to the gentle Reader by a wilful, and ſtudied, and charitable <hi>Paralepſis</hi> at the preſent.</p>
               <p>Now, Generous Sirs, weigh all theſe premiſed Conſiderations in the balances of Reaſon and Religion; and when ye have weighed their Signal Actions, 1. in Unions, 2. in Converſions, 3. in Reformations, 4. their numerous Off-ſpring, 5. their active and vigorous Atchievements, 6. their domeſtick Enemies ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, 7. their Tranſmarine Friends
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102981:27"/>and Fautors, 8. the Defects and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normities of their Competitors, &amp;c. Ye may juſtly pronounce, <hi>Euge bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſerve,</hi> to the Old Order; and, MENE, MENE: TEKEL, <hi>i. e. Ye are numbred, weighed in the balance, and found too light,</hi> even to all our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Novelliſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>Of</hi> Jus Antiquo-Anglicanum, <hi>or the old</hi> Engliſh <hi>Account.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF my Reader be of true <hi>Engliſh</hi> temper and complexion, then (beſides the aforeſaid ſignal Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Favours to the Clergy-Order) he may pleaſe to know, That 1. the Authority of the firſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King of <hi>Britain,</hi> 2. the Bond and Obligation by Oath of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kings, 3. the gracious Conceſſions of ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliaments, 4. the temper and tenour of our <hi>Engliſh Laws,</hi> 5. the Devotion of our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Gentry and Souldiery, 6. the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102981:28"/>ſad and bitter Execrations on Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants to the Order, 7. the ancient <hi>Engliſh</hi> Uſages and Cuſtoms; theſe, all theſe, are as ſo many Cords, <hi>i.e.</hi> invincible Inducements and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to bind them and their hearts and ſouls both to the Service of Gods Altar, and to all the Miniſters that attend upon it.</p>
               <p>For the Firſt; It's a bold and a blind Errour of that grand Popiſh Clerk,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellarm. de Laicis,</hi> c. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Adannos CCC. nullus in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia Christianus Princeps, i.e.</hi> There was no Chriſtian King in the world for the firſt three Centuries of years: Whiles by the ſignal mercy of the King of Kings, <hi>Lucius,</hi> the firſt Chriſtian and Baptized King, did found our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Epiſcopal Sees and Chairs by his Chriſtian, Royal and Exemplary Benevolence; and both his Baptiſm and Royal Charity did bear at leaſt ſo early a date as <hi>Anno</hi> 176.
<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Carolum R.</note> So Sir <hi>H. Spelman, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>il.</hi> Now if the firſt Chriſtian King was the Patron and <hi>Maecenas,</hi> and had the honour to <hi>love our Nation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 7.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102981:28"/>build us</hi> more then <hi>a Synagogue,</hi> will any Chriſtian <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman run to the Region of his <hi>Antipodes,</hi> and count it a great point of honour to be the <hi>Apollyon</hi> and <hi>Abaddon,</hi> the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer and ſubverter, of ſuch Noble Foundations and Endowments? This were to verifie that ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proverb, <hi>Pater noſter</hi> (God, or our King <hi>Lucius</hi>) built them, and <hi>Our Father</hi> is become the <hi>Apollyon.</hi> Every ſober <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman hath at leaſt the Loyalty and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which the very Heathen <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> had to each ſucceſſion of Kings, and to call his own <hi>Lucius</hi> his <hi>Abimelech; Pater meus Rex Lucius aedificavit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. For the Bond and Obligation by Oath of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kings; So libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and indulgent in point of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour were our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Anceſtors, that that ſacred Order hath another peculiarity and ſpecialty of Favour: which is, That all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kings, in all ſucceſſions and generations to this very day, give a treble Bond
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102981:29"/>and Obligation for defenſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection to them, even a treble Cord by the Coronation-Oath. Which is a favour not vouchſafed or deig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to any other Order and Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men. Firſt, he ſweareth <hi>to preſerve the Laws, Cuſtoms and Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes granted to the Clergy by the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Saint</hi> Edward <hi>his Predeceſſor:</hi> Then, <hi>for peace and godly agreement (according to his Power) to God, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church and Clergy:</hi> Laſtly, <hi>to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to us, and the Churches commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to our charge, all Canonical Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges,</hi> and <hi>to be Protector and Defender of the Biſhops, &amp;c.</hi> This, all this, is to be found in the Records of the Exchequer, and His Majeſties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance <hi>May</hi> 26. 1641. and in an old Manuſcript in the publick Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Oxford.</hi> And if this ſingulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of favour will ſeem an invidious and odious obſervation in ſome <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> eyes, I think there is ſomewhat correſpondent and equivalent in that Commonwealth in which there was a pure Theocraty. By act and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102981:29"/>of the King of Kings one <hi>Rod,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 17.8</note> one Tribe, even that of <hi>Levi,</hi> had <hi>buds</hi> and <hi>bloſſoms</hi> and ripe <hi>Almonds,</hi> (a treble Beniſon by miraculous mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) whileſt no ſuch fructification, no ſuch florid bleſſing, upon any or all the reſt of the Tribes in Gods <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Now let any Chriſtian Gentleman judge whether he is not a Traytor to the Kings <hi>ſoul,</hi> (his <hi>Unica,</hi> or <hi>Dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> as King <hi>David</hi> calleth it <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.20.) which ſhall perſuade him that his treble Oath is but a Gypſies knot, faſt and looſe with a breath.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The gracious Conceſſions of ſome Parliaments, ſo eminent and exemplary that they all diſclaim, and that upon Scripture-ground, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Authority to diſpoſe Clergy-eſtates.
<note place="margin">Parl. 25. <hi>Edw.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Lay-men have no authority to diſpoſe of the Goods of the Church; but (as the holy Scriptures do teſtifie) they are committed onely to the Prieſts to be diſpoſed of.</hi> And another ſaith, That <hi>the King by evil Counſellors cauſed the Temporalties of Biſhops to be ſeiſed into his hands,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. c. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>to the great damage of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102981:30"/>Biſhops: Which from henceforth ſhall not be done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The temper and tenour of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Law. In the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> (confirmed 32. times by our beſt Parliaments) it is expreſly ſaid, <hi>We have granted to God, and by this our Charter have confirmed for us and our heirs for ever, that the Church of God ſhall be free, and ſhall have her whole rights &amp; liberties inviolable. The great Charter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Part. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. proaem.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith Sir <hi>Edw. Cook, is no new Law; but it is declaratory of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal and fundamental Laws of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> And he ſaith, <hi>the Nobles and great Officers were to be ſworn to the obſervation of it.</hi> And by a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it was judged and taken as the Common Law of <hi>England.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">25 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1.</note> And (which is not unworthy your obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation) in our printed Statutes there is an heavy curſe pronounced againſt thoſe who ſhall break this grand Charter.
<note place="margin">12 <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. pag. 23.</note> Whileſt then the Souls of Kings, and Souls of Parliaments, and Souls of Nobles, and the Soul of the Law lye all at ſtake, and muſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102981:30"/>be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for the Clergy, he is a <hi>Fellow without a Soul</hi> (in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Proverb of a debauched and diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute perſon) and no Chriſtian Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, that ſtudieth and meditateth the violation and alienation of that Reverence and Maintenance.
<note place="margin">Deut. 27.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be he that removeth the ancient Land-mark. And all the people ſhall ſay, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The Devotion of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Souldiery hath been ſuch that a very ancient Biſhop, and our own Countrey-man, ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jo. Sari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b. Polychron.</hi> l. 6. c. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Jam ino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levit conſuetudo ſolennis, i. e.</hi> Even in his ancient dayes it was yet a more ancient and ſolemn uſage and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, that <hi>Eâ ipſâ die quâ militari cingulo decoratur, i. e.</hi> In that very day in which they were honoured with the badge and girdle of a Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Perſon, they took their Swords, impoſed them on the Altar of Gods Church, and made a celebrious Proteſtation of devoting both their weapons and themſelves, as the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequious Propugners of the Altar
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102981:31"/>and its Miniſters. Neither was this Superſtitious practice (as ſome would call it) without the fair prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of all the 12.
<note place="margin">Num. 2.</note> Tribes, encompaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and guarding the Tribe of God; as ſhall be evidenced in the ſequele of our Diſcourſe, touching the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiſh</hi> account.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The ſad and bitter Execrations and Imprecations againſt Malignants to the Order, are ſolemn denuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of an utter, total, final and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſeparation from God and his bleſſing, Body, Soul, Eſtate, Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and all. Ye may read the black lines of ſuch compoſed by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of that great King <hi>Edgar, apud Jo. Selden. in Notis ad Eadmerum, pag.</hi> 155, 156. They are doomed to the ſame damned end with lapſed Angels and Devils, <hi>Cain, Judas.</hi> And even theſe Curſes are but Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies drawn from the Originals and Authenticks of the meekeſt man, <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 33.11. and <hi>Darius</hi> his curſe, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 6.12. and <hi>Malachi,</hi> 3.7, <hi>ad finem.</hi> And the Curſe was even vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102981:31"/>of late dayes, according to the Prophetick Prediction of a great Sage and Judge of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Law,
<note place="margin">On the book of Statutes, <hi>Anno</hi> 51. <hi>Hen.</hi> 3.</note> That <hi>a ſacrilegious, or but ſlovenly, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion endeth commonly</hi> (as ours lately did) <hi>in downright Atheiſm.</hi> Sir <hi>Edw. Cook</hi> in <hi>Wincheſters</hi> Caſe.</p>
               <p n="7">7. For the laſt, the ancient <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Uſages and Cuſtoms; the Prieſt had ſuch eminent honour, that <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nori Thano (i. e. villae Domino, atque Militi) aequiparabatur, in cenſu capitis pariter aestimatus, pariter<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aliàs hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randus, i. e.</hi> His honour and account was in Equipage to the Lord of the Manour and Town: <hi>Spelman Praef. Concil.</hi> And again,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Selden</hi> Hiſt. c. 14. ſect. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Comes praeſidebat foro Comitatûs, non ſolus, ſed adjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus Epiſcopo; hic ut Divinum jus, ille ut Humanum diceret, alter<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> alteri conſilio eſſet &amp; auxilio. i. e.</hi> The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop and the Sheriff were Coaſſeſſors in the County-court, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Can we yet further give inſtance of ſome ſingularity and ſpecialty of favour in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conſtitutions and Canons of Charity? The Biſhop
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102981:32"/>(ſaith Sir <hi>Edw.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Part 1. fol. 86.</note> 
                  <hi>Cook) non facit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magium Regi, dicens, Ego ſum homo tuus,</hi> doth not homage even to the King, ſaying, I am your Man; <hi>ſed fidelitatem,</hi> but fealty: <hi>quia homo eſt ſolius Dei,</hi> becauſe he is the Man on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of God. The Parſon alſo, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his continual attendance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſacred Function, is freed from all perſonal charges that may hinder him in his Calling. For ſuch an one ſhall not be choſen Bayliff, Bedel, Reeve, or other ſuch Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer; nor be compelled to come to the Sheriffs Turn, to the Leets of the King or other Lords;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Finch,</hi> Of Law, book 2. c. 1. p. 88</note> and all this by the courſe of Common Law, ſaith Sir <hi>H. Finch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What a ſtrange inverſion and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of thoſe Orders from ſome mens Pride and Petulancy, who while they would ſeem to ſit on the Sunday at the feet of their Apoſtles and Teachers, yet expect to have them all the week after <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Hominum homines,</hi> in baſe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile compliances and homages to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102981:32"/>each mans humour and fancy.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, while we have had, Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Sirs, the Bond and Obligation by Oaths of Kings, Nobles, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and conſtant Cuſtoms and Uſages as declaratory, to indemnifie and ſecure the Clergies Honour and Patrimony, muſt they not even yet be inviolable &amp; intemerate? Let the Oath to poor and mean <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> by Gods own verdict and ſentence, be the end of this Controverſie. The Caſe was thus; The <hi>Gibeonites</hi> were a poor, <hi>Pagan,</hi> Heatheniſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, once devoted to deſtruction: There was yet the interpoſition of an Oath for their Indemnity; and there was an addition of a Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>à parte poſt:</hi> They were <hi>given</hi> to God (therefore called <hi>Nethinims,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezr. 2.47.</note> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to give)</hi> for the ſervice of the Temple, to be <hi>Hewers of wood,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 9.27</note> 
                  <hi>and Drawers of water:</hi> An office vile and baſe even to a Proverb, <hi>From the hewer of thy wood unto the drawer of thy water, Deut.</hi> 29.11. Yet about 400. years after, King <hi>Saul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam 21.</note> in his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102981:33"/>zele too, to pleaſe the humour of the people, ſeeking to cut aſunder all Bonds and Obligations to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable <hi>Gibeonite,</hi> God ſendeth three years Famine, and hangeth up <hi>Sauls</hi> ſeven ſons in <hi>Gibeah,</hi> for their fathers violation of that Oath. This the Verdict, this the Judgment and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution. Suppoſe ye then, Gentle Sirs, all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy to be Gods <hi>Nethinims,</hi> given to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and ſuppoſe them as vile and baſe as Hewers of wood and Draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of water: Will the ſame God that was ſo tender over poor <hi>Pagan Gibeonites,</hi> be wholly neglective of our own Chriſtian, Godly and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Prieſts and High-Prieſts, one and all? O rather let that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> prevail, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Let old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Oaths, Cuſtoms, Uſages, Lawes, Conceſſions, Execrations prevail.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:102981:33"/>
               <head>SECT. IV. Jus Iſraeliticum &amp; Moſaicum; <hi>The Iſraelitiſh account under the Law of Moſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF neither the ſignal and perſonal Merit of our old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy, nor the fair practice and precedents of our own Anceſtors will oblige, there are yet many <hi>Cords of love</hi> (as the Prophet phraſeth it) twiſted from the joynt practice of the moſt Generous, Noble and Heroick <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> in whom no guile; who lived alſo in a pure and mere Theocratie, as Gods peculiar Portion and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation.</p>
               <p>Begin we with <hi>Moſes;</hi> Whoſe own word (as Gods great Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor) might determine this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, for our more glorious Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery under the Goſpel. <hi>Moſes, the man Moſes,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>was the meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt man in all the earth, Num.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Moſes</hi> was of generous Extraction, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a fair and handſom per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102981:34"/>in the eyes of God, Acts</hi> 7.20. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes was</hi> deeply <hi>learned in all the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Aegyptians, Acts</hi> 7.22. <hi>Moſes</hi> was valiant and couragious, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ampion fourty years in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> neſs againſt all <hi>Zamzummims</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſons of <hi>Anak. Moſes</hi> alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>friend;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> the appellative of him onely and of <hi>Abraham</hi> in all the Old Teſtament. This, even this <hi>Moſes</hi> was the noble and ſingular friend of <hi>Aaron</hi> and of the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> by a ſpecialty of favour and endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This <hi>meekeſt perſon in all the earth</hi> giveth a large benediction on them, and a double execration and imprecation on all Malignants to that deſpiſed Tribe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.11. <hi>Bleſs, Lord,</hi> (not him only, but) <hi>his ſubſtance, and accept the work of his hands.</hi> And then he ſhifteth his foot from Mount <hi>Gerizzim</hi> to Mount <hi>Ebal; Smite through the loins of them that riſe againſt him, and of them that hate him, that they riſe not again.</hi> This mirrour of Gentility and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, upon Gods own record, firſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102981:34"/>falleth on curſing of ſuch <hi>Edomites;</hi> next, giveth an extenſive and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailed curſe upon the <hi>loyns</hi> of their enemies; then the fatal doom of a final and irrevocable deſtruction, praying to the God of mercies, that ſuch <hi>may never riſe again.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Go on now, ye profane world: ride on proſperouſly, ye <hi>Edomites</hi> and <hi>Zamzummims.</hi> Can theſe words be only airy and windy? Are theſe curſes but <hi>bruta fulmina?</hi> Sure I am that if it be deeply conſidered, that the holy Apoſtle fetcheth our Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Miniſtry from <hi>Aaron,</hi> Hebr. 5.4. <hi>No man taketh this honour unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron;</hi> and Goſpel-mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. and Saint <hi>Jude</hi> maketh <hi>the gain-ſaying of Core</hi> a ſin committed under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel: and,
<note place="margin">Jude 11.</note>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 33.20, 21.</note> 
                  <hi>If ye can break my Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of the day and my Covenant of the night, and that there ſhould not be day and night in their ſeaſon;</hi> even ſuch is <hi>my Covenant with the Levites and Prieſts, my Miniſters:</hi> and laſtly,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102981:35"/>if the Goſpel-Miniſtry be more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious then that of the Law, (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> giveth moſt elaborate proof and argumentation, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>per totum)</hi> I ſay, if all or any of theſe are demonſtrable, then it is more then a probability, that the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of <hi>Levi</hi>'s benediction, or the influence of that imprecation againſt his enemies, is not expired or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct even under the Meridian of our Goſpel-age. Let any generous and Chriſtian Soul firſt read the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Mount, and lay it cloſe to his Reins, and flat and plain to his Heart.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Next, I dare arraign and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent all the Tribes, not of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility only, but of the vulgar Laity alſo, in our own <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and give them another ſpecialty and patern of honour and favour in the Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratie, the Government of Gods choice and adminiſtration. Is it not, generous Sirs, highly obſervable by you, and by each called Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, that the Lord of Hoſts was ſo
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102981:35"/>tender and indulgent to the <hi>Militia togata,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 2.2. <hi>Ainſworth</hi>
                  </note> that by his ſpecial order and inſtruction the twelve Tribes were each and all of them of the Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard to the Sanctuary and to the Miniſters of the Sanctuary? <hi>Iudah, Iſſachar,</hi> and <hi>Zebulun</hi> on the Eaſt; <hi>Dan, Aſher,</hi> and <hi>Naphtali</hi> on the North; <hi>Reuben, Simeon,</hi> and <hi>Gad</hi> on the South; <hi>Ephraim, Manaſſeh,</hi> and <hi>Benjamin</hi> on the Weſt; and the Sanctuary in the midſt of them all, or <hi>in meditullio,</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> with the Prieſts and Levites immediately ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounding and encompaſſing the Sanctuary: So that the Sanctuary and the Miniſters of it were encir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cled and guarded about by the auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liary Forces of all the twelve Tribes and of all the men in the Camp. It is now offered to the option and vote of all ingenuous perſons, whether they had rather chuſe to make a breach and violation of that order, by carrying weapons not defenſive, but offenſive, to the Miniſters of the Sanctuary, or elſe become <hi>Angeli
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102981:36"/>caſtrametantes,</hi> Angels, even guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Angels, pitching their Tents round about them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſame Divine Wiſdom in his own peculiar Common-wealth, to enforce a happy aſſociation and bleſſed fraternity 'twixt Gentry and Clergy, took and ſelected ſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent perſon of the State, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other eminent perſon of the Church, and united and ſorted them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Juſt as the ſame Piety and Prudence under the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment conſorted the very Apoſtles, two and two, for the ferment and perpetuity of love and reſpect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, and to conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate a very equipage of honour from each mutually and reciprocal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<note place="margin">Exod. 17.12</note> Thus was <hi>Moſes</hi> conſorted with <hi>Aaron</hi> in the very firſt field that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his people fought; and the Lord cauſed it to be recorded <hi>ad per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuam rei memoriam,</hi> v. 14. <hi>Write this for a memorial in a Book;</hi> that the ſame courſe might for ever after be holden in all. The like uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102981:36"/>and conjugation was of <hi>Barak</hi> with <hi>Deborah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg. 4.9. Iſa. 37. 2 Chron. 20.14. 2 Kings 13.14.</note> of <hi>Hezekiah</hi> the King with <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Royal Prophet, of <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> with <hi>Iabaziel,</hi> of <hi>Ioaſh</hi> with <hi>Eliſha.</hi> Thus both the Lily and the Croſs were very conſiſtent in Gods Heraldry. And their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and reciprocal honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to each maketh them both, as the Church in the Canticles, <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribilis ſicut acies ordinata, i. e.</hi> terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to others, and amiable 'twixt themſelves, <hi>as an Army with Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, 1. the ſignal vote and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gods great Legiſlator, 2. the poſture of the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 3. the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of Sacred and Secular Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, make up King <hi>Salomons</hi> treble cord to bind and unite their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons reciprocally to each other.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is highly obſervable by the proud contemners of the Clergy, and ſingly and ſolely is an argument demonſtrative and invincible for Prieſtly honour and dignity againſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102981:37"/>all gain-ſayers of <hi>Corahs</hi> order, That <hi>cùm in omni natione certum aliquod nobilitatis argumentum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joſeph. in vita ſua.</note> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> Every Nation hath ſome particular way of ennobling, and ſome particular evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and declaration of Nobility and preeminence; as Arms for a great part is in <hi>Spain,</hi> Merchandiſe in ſome States in <hi>Italy,</hi> Learning in <hi>France,</hi> ſpecially that of Judicature: ſo Gods own peculiar Juriſdiction and Republick of the <hi>Jews</hi> was fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for the Prieſthood. A Prieſt was, even for civil priviledges and enfranchiſements, a Gentleman. Therefore hath the Apoſtle not knighted, or ennobled, but crowned every good Soul with that ſtyle, <hi>Regale Sacerdotium.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.9.</note> To be <hi>Royall</hi> without <hi>Prieſthood</hi> ſeemed not to him Dignity enough. Thus then the beſt Jewiſh Antiquary advanceth that deſpiſed Order and Profeſſion;
<note place="margin">Joſeph. in ini <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o Vitae.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> As others have other badges and cognizances of Nobility, the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:102981:37"/>Prieſthood is that amongſt us <hi>Jews:</hi> and it was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> an evidence of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſplendid and illuſtrious in that Order in the eys of God and of good men, even in Gods peculiar Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Next, it is as highly remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that in that peculiar Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Juriſdiction of God, he choſe the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> before any other, ſpecially becauſe a-kin to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> the Prince of the Congregation, and King of <hi>Jeſhurun.</hi> And <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf was at once the Son of a Prieſt and of a Prieſts Daughter, (Exod. 2.1. <hi>a man of Levi took to Wife a Daughter of Levi</hi>) and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Daughter of <hi>a Prieſt of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian,</hi> Exod. 2.16. and ſo had <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem duplicatum</hi> (in our Lawyers phraſe) with the Sacerdotal Order. O that our Engliſh Gentry would either know or believe this, who think their houſes and families diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced, and their blood ſtained and corrupted, if any of their kin become
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102981:38"/>of the Clergy. Theſe, theſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors (as Antipodes to the Divine and Moſaical Election) had rather chuſe (as <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the Son of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat</hi>) of <hi>the loweſt of the people,</hi> then of the higheſt of their own kindred. But (God be thanked) neither <hi>God</hi> nor <hi>Moſes</hi> were once of their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. How far diſtant and diſſonant, how diametrically oppoſite to God and <hi>Moſes</hi> were they who would not have the Croſs (the Emblem of Church and Church-men) in any conjunction with the Lily (the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of the State) in the Kingly or Royal Arms! As if it were a huge diminution and abatement of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for <hi>Levi</hi> to have the leaſt rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Moſes;</hi> though <hi>Moſes</hi> had his Father a Levite, his Mother a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Levi,</hi> and his Wife too a daughter of a Prieſt in <hi>Midian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. There is yet another thing not of inferiour conſideration to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers precedent. The rule of <hi>Jews</hi> is,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> l. 2. c. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Siquis lanio, aut tonſor, aut coriari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, &amp;c.</hi> No Butcher, or Slaughter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102981:38"/>no Barber, or Weaver, or Tanner, &amp;c. ſhall at any hand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Prieſt. Not that the Arts themſelves were unholy or illegiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate; <hi>Sed quod eb corum ſordes po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus in cujuſvis ſucceſsione non ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſceret: i. e.</hi> The holy people of God, his Saints, would never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce in ſo ſordid a ſucceſſion. A good patern in the <hi>Sinai</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> for the real Saints of God in the mount <hi>Sion</hi> of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="7">7. The Miniſters of Gods own pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Dioceſe have this title and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation from Gods own mouth, and in his own Heraldry, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> either actively, <hi>favourable, benigne, graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous;</hi> or paſſively, <hi>highly favoured,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 33.12.</note> 
                  <hi>highly graced by Jehovah. Let thy Urim and thy Thummim be with thy favourite,</hi> or <hi>favoured one,</hi> Deut. 33.8. In the Goſpel there is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the very Function, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.8. So that both Old and New Teſtament do ſign and ſeal and exhibit a near relation, a ſpecialty and ſingularity of favour from God
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102981:39"/>and all good men. All the people are ſometimes called Gods <hi>peculiar;</hi> but theſe, the peculiar Tribe of a peculiar people. As the Bleſſed Virgin hath a word new-minted and coyned by the Angel, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.28. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a word not found in any either Ethnick or Eccleſiaſtick Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor; ſo, as if all the Clergy were in ſome meaſure ſons of the Bleſſed Virgin, they are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly favoured by Jehovah,</hi> and the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of <hi>Jehovah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. In the laſt place; the very laſt Prophet in all <hi>Iſrael</hi> is another <hi>Boanerges,</hi> (beſides them in the New Teſtament) ſpeaketh thunder and lightning againſt all Malignants to that Sacred Order in all Ages. <hi>Will a man rob God?</hi> an emphatical inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation. Will an <hi>Edomite, Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kite, Philiſtine,</hi> or any <hi>man, rob God?</hi> or, <hi>will</hi> he <hi>rob,</hi> or <hi>kick, his own God?</hi> ſo the LXX. render it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>Will he ſupplant,</hi> or <hi>caſt his own God under feet,</hi> as it were? The ſacrilegious contempt of Prieſts
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102981:39"/>endeth in downright <hi>Atheiſm;</hi> as Sir <hi>Edw. Cook</hi> before told us. Next, there is pertinacy and obſtinacy in thoſe Malignants: They plead, <hi>Not guilty,</hi> to the Worlds end; <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in have we robbed thee?</hi> God aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the propriety; Ye have rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed me <hi>in Tithes and Offerings, i.e.</hi> in detaining what ſhould ſupport my Servants and Service: So <hi>Deodate</hi> of <hi>Geneva,</hi> and Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> of old, <hi>in Mal.</hi> 3.8. And after all, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt is hereditary and ancient, <hi>even from the days of your Fathers,</hi> v. 7. After arraignment and endictment God proceedeth to ſentence; <hi>Ye are curſed with a curſe,</hi> becauſe ye have thus robbed me, <hi>even this whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> v. 9. It ſeemeth, though they were Gods peculiar people, yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, many ſuch enemies there were to his <hi>highly-favoured</hi> Levi. Yet one good expedient there is for that and all Nations after it: v. 10. <hi>Bring in all the Tithes,—prove me if I will not open the windows of heaven, and pour you out a bleſsing, that there ſhall
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102981:40"/>not be room enough to receive it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus God in his own Dioceſe <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth good meaſure</hi> of favour and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to his Prieſts, <hi>preſſed down, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken together, and running over;</hi> whileſt our Engliſh Proverb ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our Engliſh ſenſe, <hi>It is well when it pincheth on the Parſons ſide.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V. Jus Evangelicum; <hi>The Evangelical Account, under the Goſpel.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe great <hi>Shepherd</hi> and <hi>Biſhop of Souls,</hi> the <hi>holy</hi> and <hi>harmleſs Prieſt, ſeparated from ſinners,</hi> maketh ſome ſpecial, peculiar and eminent reward belonging to a Prophet, <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus,</hi> and <hi>co nomine,</hi> as a Prophet: <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.41. <hi>He ſhall receive a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets reward, i.e.</hi> a ſignal and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable recompence. Otherwiſe our Saviours ſpeech hath no edge, no enforcement in it at all. Thus Chriſts own Angel preacheth us his Doctrine; <hi>Thoſe that be wiſe ſhall
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:102981:40"/>ſhine as the brightneſſe of the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; i.e.</hi> all ſons of light,
<note place="margin">Dan. 12.3</note> all ſons of wiſdom: <hi>But thoſe that turn ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unto righteouſneſſe, i.e.</hi> Teachers and Inſtructers, <hi>as the Stars for ever and ever; i. e.</hi> A greater knot and union, a happy conſtellation of light and glory ſhall be upon them. There is yet an additional and accumulate glory and eminency from the tongue of Chriſts Angel;
<note place="margin">Dan. 12.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Go thy way, Daniel: for thou ſhalt rest, and ſtand up in thy Lot at the end of days.</hi> IN SORTE TUA, <hi>i. e. in ſorte Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetarum,</hi> that is, the moſt noble and gallant portion and ſtation, as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> interpreteth it. Our great <hi>Rabbi</hi> then ſigneth and ſealeth a warrant, <hi>Teſte meipſo,</hi> Matth. 10.41. That any Patron, Fautor or <hi>Gaius</hi> to a Prieſt or Prophet ſhall have a glorious in-come or revenue for his expences. For <hi>he that receiveth a Prophet</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> relieveth and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth, ſupporteth and fomenteth a Prophet) <hi>ſhall be partaker of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets reward.</hi> The ground and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:102981:41"/>is evident; Becauſe each Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour and Fomenter of a Prophet hath an intereſt in and influence upon the work, and conſequently hath a kind of title and entail upon the reward that appertaineth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The great Biſhop of Soules, though he himſelf were a <hi>Prieſt holy, harmleſs, undefiled, and ſeparated from ſinners,</hi> yet vouchſafeth a <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamins</hi> portion of reſpect and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the Function and Order, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then when it was debaſed and almoſt deſecrated by the enormous crimes and perſonal unworthineſs of thoſe that were inveſted and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>augurated in the Prieſthood. And this ſingular zeal ſhould be highly obſervable, and made exemplary to Zealots of a quite contrary tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and diſpoſition. His indulgence and condeſcenſion to the worſt Prieſts is very legible Mark 1.44. <hi>Vade, &amp; oſtende te Sacerdoti, &amp; offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</hi> Is our holy Lord and Maſter a <hi>Macenas</hi> and Patron even to ſuch
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:102981:41"/>Prieſts? Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> giveth the Doctrine upon that Text:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> 65.</note> 
                  <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntificibus &amp; Sacerdotibus hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ſervavit, quamvis illi nec timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Dei nec agnitionem Chriſti ſervaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: i. e.</hi> That pure, holy and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled Prieſt hath a fair reſerve of honour even to thoſe that reſerved no fear of God nor honour of Chriſt himſelf. Sure it is ſtrange, that the pretended zealous Diſciples of Chriſt ſhould in this point or matter become <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, wholly <hi>oppoſite,</hi> both to Chriſt and ſuch unworthy Prieſts at once.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 55.</note> And the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth both heighten and ſtrengthen that obſervation by St. <hi>Pauls</hi> example:
<note place="margin">Act. 22.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Noſciebam quia Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifex eſt: ſcriptum eſt enim, Principem populi tui non maledices:</hi> That, <hi>quamvis impii, ſacrilegi, cruenti,</hi> though impious, ſacrilegious, blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Prieſts, <hi>nil praeter inane nomen &amp; umbram,</hi> no real, Sacerdotal ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and authority, yet, <hi>Vade, oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, offerto,</hi> Go, ſhew to the Prieſt, and offer to him. Neither did our
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:102981:42"/>Lord only reſerve reſpect and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the external and Judaical Prieſts, but (which is far more) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to his own menial and dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Apoſtle: <hi>Judas, quamvis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus pecuniam dominicam diſpenſavit, non malam nec inutilem bene accipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entibus fecit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Contra Petilian.</hi> 3.</note> as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it: <hi>i. e.</hi> Though <hi>Judas</hi> had the honour of being Steward or Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of Chriſts houſe, his foul hands did not corrupt or embaſe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters charity to the poor. Another Father ſpeaketh for veneration of the Order even in the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy perſons:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ephr. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotio,</hi> p. 20.</note> As Gold or a Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el is ſtill Gold and pretious when it falleth into the very Mire or Dirt; <hi>fic nec Sacerdotium ſordidum redditur, quamvis indignus ſit qui illud recipit; i. e.</hi> ſo the Prieſthood is not baſe, though the Prieſt be unworthy. The like Doctrine with that of the great Biſhop of Souls and our Lord and Maſter, is taught by <hi>Iſidore</hi> of <hi>Pelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſium, Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3. and by St. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd, Serm.</hi> 3. <hi>de Adventu Dom.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:102981:42"/>
               <p n="3">3. While Sacrilege, <hi>i. e.</hi> the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Perſons, Things, Places ſacred, is eſteemed in this laſt and worſt age a venial ſin, or no ſin at all, I find no one Sin whatſoever hath ſuch an exemplary and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous hatred declared from God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, as that <hi>peccadillo</hi> in the eyes of fleſh and blood. It is a ſin againſt which Gods vengeance hath ſmoaked by ſpecial and ſignal judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and penalties, no leſs then four or five times <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e.</hi> in the very moment or inſtant of its commiſſion, even <hi>flagrante crimine,</hi> as they ſay. And let the beſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of that ſin even <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſearch and dig from the <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies</hi> or ſurface of the Scripture to the very bottom of it, and he ſhall not find a parallel vengeance upon any <hi>ſpecies</hi> or ſort of ſins. Doth <hi>Uzziah</hi> intrude into and violate the ſacred Order?
<note place="margin">2 Chron. 26.20. Num. 16.</note> His Leproſie is Gods<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token ſent him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Do <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> and his Complices equalize and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:102981:43"/>level themſelves with the ſacred Prieſts <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons? The vengeance of the God of Heaven openeth the earth, and giveth a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble miracle of wrath, and thoſe ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and contemporary with the ſin. Doth <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> with his thouſand Princes, though heathen only, violate and abuſe the ſacred cups and uten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſils? He is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſmitten with trembling: which was Gods-token on <hi>Cain</hi> alſo for the ſame enormity. Thus God the Father is at the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of more fatal and mortal miracles againſt this ſin then any other of the firſt or ſecond magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</p>
               <p>Our Lord and Maſter,
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.14. Joh. 8.11.</note> the ſecond Perſon, waveth giving any ſentence or judgement in the caſe of Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and in the caſe of Adultery; but he paſſeth ſentence and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and penalty <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt the violaters of his Houſe, and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers and murtherers of his <hi>Zecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah</hi> and his Succeſſors. His whip of ſmall Cords,
<note place="margin">In Mat. 21</note> as Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:102981:43"/>wrought a greater miracle then any in the whole Goſpel; <hi>Quòd unu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>homo, &amp; illo tempore contemtibilis, &amp;c. potuerit ad unius flagelli verbera tantam ejicere multitudinem, &amp;c.</hi> Such is our great Biſhops fiery zele and indignation, that he himſelf is both Accuſer, Witneſs, Judge and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner; which is very ſingular, in that caſe alone.
<note place="margin">Mat. 21. &amp; Joh. 2.</note> And this miracle alſo is doubled (as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Dream) and acted twice over, for the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and confirmation and ratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it to all enſuing Ages and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, as <hi>Grotius in Joh.</hi> 2.14. and Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> obſerve. So that Chriſt made it both the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> of his Epiſcopal care and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, the Spirit of Chriſt, the third Perſon, by the mouth of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> puniſheth the fraudulent ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reption of things Sacred from the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nds and feet of the Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">Acts 5.</note> in <hi>Ananias's</hi> and <hi>Saphira's</hi> caſe. While now, Generous and Courteous Sirs, the bleſſed Trinity hath vouchſafed
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:102981:44"/>a double Trinity of Miracles (par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the Phraſe) as ſo many Pillars of Salt to ſeaſon the memories of all poſterity, what Chriſtian can ſooth and flatter himſelf in the innocent nature of ſuch ſins? Though no ſuch miraculous productions of Divine Providence did yeſterday or to day appear from the hands of Father, Son, or Holy Ghoſt; yet <hi>theſe were written for</hi> our <hi>example,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and</hi> are <hi>for our admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. After the great Biſhop of Souls, let the great Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> produce his ſtrongeſt zele for the honourable ſupport and ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſacred Order to the worlds end. He uſeth a double Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: <hi>A Minori</hi> firſt, <hi>à Jumentis;</hi> The Ox not to be muzzled, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.9. Yet higher, from men that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in carnal works; <hi>If we ſow unto you ſpiritual things, is it</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a great matter, if we reap your carnal things? ver.</hi> 11. I obſerve that the ſame St. <hi>Paul</hi> giveth out an Injunction,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102981:44"/>
                  <hi>Let him that is taught communicate</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>in all good things, Gal.</hi> 6.6. And if the Compenſation be onely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, though <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, yet in his liberal eye thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are but a ſmall recompence for our Paſtoral pains: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Is it a great matter if we reap, &amp;c.</hi> In Gods own Law the inferiour office and functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a <hi>Levite</hi> (that was <hi>Plebs &amp; vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus Cleri</hi>) was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, no ſmall thing: <hi>Is it a ſmall thing that God hath ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated you</hi> (even <hi>Levi</hi>) <hi>from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation? Num.</hi> 16.9. But in the liberality and magnificence of the Goſpel-Spirit, if ye give <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>all your carnal things,</hi> it muſt not be written down and put into ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a great matter.</hi> And yet the diſcharge of that little debt is a ſore burden to break ſome mens ſleeps, and backs, and hearts alſo; though an Apoſtle inſtructeth them, that <hi>for us to reap their carnal things,</hi> is not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, no <hi>great matter.</hi> By a juſt and true and modeſt col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of both Texts, <hi>Num.</hi> 16.9.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:102981:45"/>with <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6. it is an evident con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, That the loweſt Office of Miniſtery is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>great</hi> in Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, whileſt the greateſt honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by carnal and temporal things is not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>any great matter</hi> in Gods own eys. Let not then <hi>thine eye be evil, becauſe Gods is good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The great Saint <hi>Paul</hi> again, who one while is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">Eph. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>leſs then the leaſt of Saints,</hi> in his own Heraldry and account, yet elſewhere uſeth a word of pregnancy, an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbole and ſuperſoetation of honour and reſpects to the ſacred Order of Miniſters; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to eſteem them very highly in love,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.13. a compounded, decompounded and ſuperlative ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> noteth Abundance, yea Superfluity: So <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.21. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> maketh ſome addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and augmentation. But <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeaketh an exceeding, exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and ſuperlative degree of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. As the ſame Saint <hi>Paul</hi> by his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 Theſ. 3.10.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102981:45"/>
                  <hi>praying exceedingly,</hi> intimateth the exceſſive and conſtant and violent fervency of his Apoſtolick affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in begging the bleſſing of God on the ſame <hi>Theſſalonians.</hi> Now where the Holy Ghoſt addeth one <hi>Iota</hi> or tittle in the Book of God, it is not to be accounted idle, fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous or ſuperfluous. For (as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> excellently) <hi>Si nec folium de arbore, nec unus è paſſerculis cadit, &amp;c.</hi> If not a leaf falleth from any tree, nor a Sparrow from the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top, without the providence of our Heavenly Father, ſure not one <hi>apex</hi> or <hi>Iota</hi> falleth from the Spirit of Wiſdom without a wiſe and juſt and provident election. Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> choice word doth therefore ſoberly and gravely ſignifie, according to that Rhetorical <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <hi>Incremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> (as <hi>Caſaubon</hi> calleth it) of his and our Lord and Maſter,
<note place="margin">Luk 6.38.</note> even <hi>good meaſure</hi> of honour and reſpects, <hi>preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed down, ſhaken together,</hi> and <hi>running over,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. That as in the Office and Function of a Biſhop he
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:102981:46"/>culleth out and ſelecteth a word of moſt exquiſite and accurate ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and <hi>emphaſis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 1.5.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſet in order the things that are wanting,</hi> &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſingly and ſolely, is <hi>to make ſtraight</hi> or <hi>right;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to do it; and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to do it not only exactly, but over and over again. As thus in the diſcharge and execution of the Work and Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there ſhould be exactneſs and accurateneſs <hi>ex parte Epiſcopi;</hi> ſo in the retribution and remune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of that Office there is a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of honour, of love, of reſpects, <hi>ex parte Laici.</hi> And as the ſame Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith perſonally of himſelf, that he doth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not onely ſtretch himſelf to the fulneſs of his meaſure,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.14.</note> but, as it were, tentour himſelf far beyond his ſcantling, to do ſervice to the Church of God; ſo would he have a compounded and ſuper-compounded love and honour from thoſe he ſo ſerveth, &amp; the Pupils of that holy tuition. Yet
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:102981:46"/>once more, the very ſame Apoſtle in the abundance of affliction, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and diſreputation from an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful world hath another high ſuperlative,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.4.</note>, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a ſuperabundance of joy</hi> even in the midſt of thoſe ſorrows. An excellent Lecture, which containeth both Doctrine and Uſe of Joy and Comfort to that holy Order of men in their moſt abject and deſpicable condition for Chriſts ſake. Lord, give me and all of us <hi>utramvis fortunae paginam,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſupereffluence of their love and honour, or elſe a compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and decompounded joy and comfort under their diſhonour and diſgraces. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Let it not ſeem ſtrange, or a prodigious piece of pride, if the Eccleſiaſtick Miniſter claimeth, even <hi>jure Divine,</hi> at leaſt a <hi>Gavel-kind</hi> of honor with, or above the civil or ſecular Magiſtrate. It is certainly true that the ſecular Magiſtrates even in Scripture-idiome and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:102981:47"/>are called <hi>Elders,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as when we read of <hi>the Elders of Iſrael, the Elders of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, the Elders of the People.</hi> By which way the notion of the words 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. may juſtly and truly be conſtrued by way of <hi>tranſit us à Theſi ad Hypotheſin,</hi> as Rhetoricians call it, thus, <hi>Cùm omnes Seniores, ſive Reip. ſive Eccleſiae, duplici honore dignandi ſunt, tamen</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè, Seniores Eccleſiaſtici, qui labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in verbo &amp; doctrina i.e.</hi> Whileſt all Elders deſerve double honour, ſpecially and ſignally the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Elders do, that labour in the Word and Doctrine. In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of that ſame Chapter, <hi>Elder</hi> is uſed in that larger and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſenſe; <hi>Rebuke not an Elder, but exhort him as a Father; the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Women as Mothers.</hi> And why not here ſo alſo, for a civil Elder? And both the one and the other were in place of the Firſt-born; and therefore a double honour was due to each promiſcuouſly and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:102981:47"/>indefinitely; becauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is not Alms, but Tribute of honour from the inferiour to the ſuperiour, and of the ſame nature with honour to Princes and Magiſtrates. If that expoſition ſeemeth too ſupercili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſtately for the honour of Church-men, yet it ſeemeth to be <hi>ſecundum cor Dei,</hi> Pſal. 87.2. <hi>The Lord loveth the gates of Zion</hi> (where the Temple was ſumptuouſly and magnificently built, and many Schools of the Prophets erected) <hi>more then all the dwellings of Jacob.</hi> And upon this account it was a <hi>Pſalm or Song for the Sons of Korah, i. e.</hi> men of ſacred Order; yet might it be ſung by them without any tumour or ſuperciliouſneſſe of ſpiritual pride. According to the <hi>genius</hi> of the ſweet Singer of <hi>Iſrael, ſecundum cor Davidis,</hi> alſo, <hi>I had rather be a Door-keeper in the houſe of God, (i. e.</hi> a Lazar at the Door, or one of the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the ancient Chriſtian Church) <hi>then to dwell in any Tents of ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102981:48"/>i. e.</hi> to be a Centurion or Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarch in tents ſecular and civil. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it fareth with the aforeſaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of the three aforeſaid Texts, yet it is an indubitate truth that the <hi>Quota pars</hi> of Reverence and Maintenance is thus far deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and definite, even <hi>jure Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> to wit, <hi>double Honour.</hi> And that exalteth and advanceth as high as the ſtate and condition of the Firſt-born: which ſoundeth too high and lofty for the tender eares of this Age: for it clearly involveth Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Dominion and Juriſdiction; and therefore concludeth at leaſt a participation of honour (if not the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) with the Civil Magiſtrate himſelf.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Laſtly, If any of you will needs vilifie that which our great Maſter Chriſt and his great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle do ſo magnifie; let us know then what it is thou doſt magnifie and make a juſt account of. Is the whole myſtical body of Chriſt great in thine eyes?
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:102981:48"/>Why, the Miniſtry is moſt imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſerviceable <hi>for the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the body of Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 4.11, 12.</note> Is it thine own Soul thou magnifieſt? Why, in Scripture-phraſe, <hi>qui ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem erudit, dicitur Animas facere,</hi> he that teacheth, <hi>maketh,</hi> or <hi>gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, Souls.</hi> Thus, <hi>Animas quas fecerant in Charran,</hi> Gen. 12.5. <hi>the ſouls which they had gotten in Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran.</hi> FECERANT, <hi>hoc eſt, Deo lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifecerant,</hi> Souls which they had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed and reduced to God. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is it Gods grace and Spirit thou canſt magnifie? Why, while the Phyſician is but <hi>Miniſter Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> and the Lawyer and honourable Counſellor is <hi>Miniſter Juſtitia,</hi> the other is <hi>Miniſter Gratia</hi> and Miniſter of the Spirit. It is a rare and ſingular obſervation, which I never found but in one Author, and he one that lived above a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſond years ſince, touching the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luckineſs of the Miniſtery. It is <hi>Iſidorus Peluſiota,</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Zoſimus</hi> and <hi>Maro</hi> and <hi>Euſtathius,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:102981:49"/>three ſcandalous and obnoxious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of his time. <hi>There is this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>betwixt</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Eccleſiaſtical, and Miniſters and Magiſtrates ſecular: If theſe offend, the whole world can diſtinguiſh betwixt their Perſons and their Functions. No diſparagement falleth upon any but the offenders. But if Eccleſiaſtical perſons become obnoxious, then</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>they confound their Perſons and their Functions, and transfer the ſhame of the faults of ſome even upon all, yea upon the whole Order it ſelf.</hi> Which is a practice too diſ-ingenuous &amp; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt for the candor and lenity and gentleneſs of any of your generous and Chriſtian Order. Theſe may tranſcribe a better Copy from that great Patron of the Clergy and Martyr of the Church: <hi>I am,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſo much a friend to all Church-men that have any thing in them beſeeming that ſacred Function, that I have hazarded mine own Intereſts,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:102981:49"/>chiefly upon Conſcience and conſtancy to maintain their Rights. — I muſt confeſs, I bear with more grief and impatience the want of my Chaplains then of any other my Servants, and next (if not beyond in ſome things) to the being ſequeſtred from my Wife and Children, ſince from theſe indeed more of humane and temporary affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but from thoſe more of heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and eternal improvements may be expected.</hi> Sic Carolus Magno ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor in 24. Sect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:102981:50"/>
               <head>SECT. VI. Jus Eccleſiaſticum; <hi>The Eccleſiaſtick Primitive Account.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen in the Old Teſtament <hi>Shechem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 34.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Hamors</hi> ſon, by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Expreſs and Heraldry <hi>was more honourable then all the houſe of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> becauſe he received the badge and cogniſance of Religion; and when in the New Teſtament the men of <hi>Beraea</hi> were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>more noble and generous,</hi> of a better kind and ſtock, <hi>then thoſe of Theſſalonica, becauſe they received the Word</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>with all readineſs of mind;</hi> by a parity of Reaſon and Religion thoſe are the moſt noble and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Chriſtians, ancient or modern, which <hi>receive a Prophet in nomine Prophetae,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>with all promptneſs</hi> and propenſeneſs of love and reſpects.</p>
               <p>In the Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ritual Heraldry of Holy Writ, we find the very Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">Heb. 5.4.</note> 
                  <hi>very Honour;</hi> yet
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:102981:50"/>more, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(a) 1 Tim. 5.17.</note>; yet further, <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent and ſuperlative ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(b) 1 Theſ. 5.13.</note> is their due and debt: And the expreſſe title of <hi>Lord</hi> is given to
<note place="margin">(c) 1 Kings 18.7, 13.</note> one; and to others, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">(d) Acts 15.22. Heb. 13.17, 24.</note>, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">(e) 1 Tim. 5.17.</note>, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">(f) Rom. 12.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Xenoph. l.</hi> 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Summus belli Capitaneus,</hi> Id. l. 7.</note>, <hi>Leaders, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, Dukes,</hi> yea <hi>Stars</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(g) Rev. 1.20.</note> and <hi>Angels</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(h) Rev. 1.20. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.1, 8, 12, 18. &amp; 3.1, 7, 14.</note>; Titles of not inferiour Alloy to <hi>Lord Biſhop.</hi> Thus far we have an Indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity by the Act and Writ of the great Biſhop of Souls. And the guiſe and mode of ancient Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom was, boldly to tranſcribe the Copy from ſo fair and authentick an Original. St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> to thoſe of <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>yrna, Honora Epiſcopum, ut Principem Sacerdotum, imaginem Dei ferentem;</hi> that is, <hi>Honour the Biſhop, as the Prince of the Prieſts, and as bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the image of God.</hi> Nothing more cuſtomary and faſhionable with pure Antiquity, then to ſpeak of them with honourable Appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives:
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:102981:51"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Moſt honourable Lords; Gods-beloved Lords; Most holy,</hi> The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoret, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4, <hi>&amp;</hi> 5. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 9. and, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Father in God,</hi> as <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexand. edit. Binii,</hi> p. 227. And becauſe abſtractive terms are moſt ſignificant and emphatical, they were very prodigal of ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faces of honor and reſpects. Thus the noble <hi>Voluſianus, Illuſtris Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(a) <hi>Aug. epiſt.</hi> 3.</note>, beſpeaketh the great Biſhop of little <hi>Hippo</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(b) <hi>Ep.</hi> 2.</note>, <hi>Incolumem Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationem veſtram ſumma Divinitas tueatur,</hi> that is, <hi>The ſacred Majeſty and Divinity protect and defend your ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable perſon.</hi> Yea, even St. <hi>Hierom</hi> himſelf, an ancient Presbyter, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (a young Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop to him) <hi>Beatitudin is veſtra lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 13.</note>, ſaith he, <hi>The Letters of your Bleſſedneſs,</hi> or <hi>Benediction.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 53.</note> 
                  <hi>Incolumem Sanctitatem tuam Divinitas tueatur,</hi> that is, <hi>Let the Majeſty of heaven defend your Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> In the <hi>Epheſine</hi> Council
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil. Biaii, tom.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 237, <hi>&amp;</hi> 177, <hi>&amp;</hi> 178.</note> to <hi>Neſtorius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:102981:51"/>they uſe theſe honourable Titles; — <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. — <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. — <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. — <hi>thy Holineſs, — thy San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity, — thy Reverence.</hi> And when <hi>Chariſius,</hi> an obſequious Presbyter, maketh his addreſs and application to the whole Convocation
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tom.</hi> 2.359.</note>, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>For this cauſe I proſtrate my ſelf before your Sanctity.</hi> And the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and reverend St. <hi>Hierom</hi> thus taketh his leave of St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Vale, aetate fili, dignitate parens,</hi> that is, <hi>Farewel, my Son in age, my Father in honour</hi> and in God. I ſhall cloſe and conclude this <hi>Sorites</hi> and Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation of Honour with St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms</hi> obſervation, very proper and pertinent to our Age,
<note n="*" place="margin">El. Pſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.</note> 
                  <hi>Haeretici à diabolo honorum vocabula Epiſcopis non dare didicerunt,</hi> that is, <hi>Hereticks</hi> (not true Chriſtians) <hi>have learned f the Devil, not to give due Titles of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to Biſhops.</hi> An angry word of a Patriarch. In a parallel obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> obſerving how tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r and curious our bleſſed Saviour was,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:102981:52"/>that he might give honour to the Prieſts even of the <hi>Jews,</hi> even then when their malice was hot, as ſet on fire by Hell, againſt him, <hi>Docuit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Sacerdotes veros legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè &amp; plenè honorari, dum circa falſos Sacerdotes ipſe talis exſtitit,</hi> that is, <hi>He taught how lawful and plentiful ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ought to be rendred to true Biſhops and Miniſters, when ſuch</hi> honour was given <hi>even to falſe Prieſts</hi> by the beſt Biſhop of Souls.</p>
               <p>In the next place, as their Titles throughout Chriſtendom were glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and magnificent, ſo their Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions and Patrimony were not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurious and deſpicable. The great Biſhop of little <hi>Hippo,</hi> though he was extracted <hi>ex nobili proſapia,</hi> of a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtock or family,
<note place="margin">In vita Auguſtini.</note> as <hi>Poſsidonius</hi> writeth, yet had ſuch a full and fat Eccleſiaſtical Patrimony and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 225.</note> that himſelf ſaith, <hi>Vix vigeſimâ particulâ res mea paterna exiſtimari poteſt in comparatione praediorum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae quae nunc, ut Eccleſiae dominus, exiſtimor poſsidere;</hi> His noble and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:102981:52"/>natural fathers Eſtate and Patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was no better then the twentieth part of what he enjoyed as Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the Church. Yet in his greateſt eminence and affluence his friends and foes alſo were his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgators,
<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Nullâ nos cupiditate pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae in rebus Eccleſiaſticis ſordidari,</hi> that he was not debaſed and dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate by any unhandſom concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence toward Mammon. The moſt Great and moſt Chriſtian <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> and the firſt Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, had ſo gracious and liberal an eye to Church men, that (as our <hi>Lucius</hi> in <hi>England) Ex ſtatuis Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicis pretioſioris materiae pecunias con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flavit, &amp; Eccleſiis contulit,</hi> that is,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> l.</hi> 2. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> He ſpoiled the Heathen, as <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>coyned the moſt precious ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of their Idols into currant mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and gave it</hi> to the Servants and Serv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces of the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Yea,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sozom l.</hi> 1. c. 8. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 5. <hi>c</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>ex publicis tributis per ſingulas civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp;c.</hi> He made an augmentation from publick Tributes, as Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and Honoraries to the preſent
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:102981:53"/>Church-men, and made them a firm conveyance and perpetuity by an eſtabliſhed Law.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de vita conſtant.</hi>
                  </note> And if any dyed either Inteſtate or without an Heir, his Eſtate was given as a Congiary to the <hi>Aerarium Eccleſiaſticum.</hi> The Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> had likewiſe <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rima vaſa,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>et. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>anathemata &amp; pecunias,</hi> many precious Utenſils, Riches and Offerings, from the ſame liberal hand. Nay, his Magnificence was ſo eminent and exemplary to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Church-order, that they were no leſs then Commoners at the Emperors Table:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de vit. Con.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> inſomuch that ſome envious and diſaffected perſons <hi>verbo Ironico Pupillum Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſiae nominarent,</hi> that is, in our modern Phraſe, <hi>He was Prieſt-ridden,</hi> and <hi>a very Pupil and Ward</hi> to ſuch Spiritual Tutors. Of the ſame temper and <hi>genius</hi> was another Emperor, <hi>Theodoſius;</hi> ſo charitable &amp; obſervant of men of Sacred Order, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Secrat. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> &amp;c. <hi>He did not onely abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honour Prieſts of his own faith and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:102981:53"/>perſuaſion, but the very Novatian Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops alſo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One Primitive Biſhop,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sozom. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Acacius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Beraea,</hi> gave this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, this <hi>evidence and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of excellent vertue,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>all his life long his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal See and Houſe was an open houſe for all comers of the City.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could eaſily give a <hi>Galeed,</hi> a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heap, of Witneſſes from Primitive Chriſtians: but I will not further tempt and over-lay the patience of any generous Reader.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII. Jus Naturale, <hi>from thoſe under the Law of Nature, either Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal or Ethnical.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe light and law of Nature, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Patriarchs and refined Ethnicks, made their Prieſts or Miniſters of a ſplendid and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable account and condition. This
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:102981:54"/>Law of Nature, as well as the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> and of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is expreſly ſtyled <hi>the Law of God,</hi> Exod. 15.26. &amp; 18.16. when as yet the Law was not given in <hi>Sinai.</hi> And ſo alſo by Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Goſpel-Divinity it is ſaid of Heathens, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14. that <hi>they are a law to themſelves,</hi> and that <hi>the Law is written in their Hearts,</hi> v. 15. Thus it is ſaid of Tithes and Firſt-fruits, the Honoraries of the Prieſt, <hi>Non tardabis,</hi> Exod. 22.29. <hi>Thou ſhalt not keep back,</hi> materially to be conſidered, evidently ſhewing it was a cuſtom of old before the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical Law. So <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.21. <hi>Non tardabis,</hi> that is, <hi>Thou ſhalt not be ſlack to pay, viz.</hi> what was then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready due.</p>
               <p>It is confeſſedly true on all hands, that among Patriarchs the firſt-born was the Prieſt, and ſo Head and Lord and Prince of the whole Family. On this account <hi>Jacob</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Reuben, primum in donis,</hi> i. e. <hi>in ſacrificiis offerendis,</hi> Gen. 49.3. By right of primogeniture the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotal
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:102981:54"/>Function was <hi>Reubens.</hi> The firſt-born <hi>terminis terminantibus</hi> are called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Sacerdotes,</hi> Exod. 19.22. And this honour infallibly was <hi>vel ab ipſo Deo, vel ab Adamo Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus S. inſtinctu,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Miniſt. p.</hi> 235.</note> as learned <hi>Gerhard</hi> ſaith, <hi>either by Gods own aſsignation and deſignment, or by Adam from the Spirit of God.</hi> Now the Firſt-born was, Firſt, higher then his Brethren, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.27. next in honour to his Parents, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.3. Secondly, had a double portion of his Fathers goods, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.17. beſides his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance; Thirdly, ſucceeded in Government of Family or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.3. And, fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in the adminiſtration of Prieſt-hood and ſervice of God, <hi>Num.</hi> 8.14,—17. And theſe were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Exod.</hi> 6.25. <hi>Heads of the Fathers,</hi> Arch-Prieſts, or Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual.</p>
               <p>Under this Meridian of the light of Nature <hi>Melchizedek,</hi> though he had even Royal Revenues and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, yet as an acceſſion of juſt
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:102981:55"/>honour received <hi>Tithes</hi> and <hi>Gifts</hi> from <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 14.20. Sure then a noble, ſplendid and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent honour was not judged incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible by the grand Sages of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, either <hi>Melchizedek,</hi> or <hi>Abram,</hi> or <hi>Jacob.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The laſt Prophet of the Old Teſtament carrieth an <hi>Angel</hi> or <hi>Meſſenger</hi> of God in his very name, <hi>MALACHI.</hi> And this Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Doctor, to confute the ſordid and ſacrilegious <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth an Argument or Topick from the very Ethnick devotion, <hi>Ch.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Will a man rob his God?</hi> Will an Heathen, an Amalekite, Philiſtine, Aethiopian, or any man rob his God? Any Miniſter or Meſſenger of the New Teſtament may as juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly argue from the ſame Topick a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any Sons or Patrons that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud their Prieſt Evangelical, <hi>Will a man rob his own God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Sacred Regiſter we finde an high and honourable account from Heathen and Exotick Nations.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:102981:55"/>Even <hi>Philiſtines</hi> by the light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would conſult and deliberate with ſacred Perſons in things Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine. Even when Princes of <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> (which is not a little remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able) had before given their own votes and voices, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.11. they afterwards conſulted with their <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Southſayers,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.2. And thoſe ſacred (yet prophane) Prieſts would not have <hi>Gods own Ark go away empty,</hi> v. 3. What a ſhame then and opprobry is it for Chriſtian Magiſtrates to aſſume a Monopoly of Votes and Suffrages to diſpoſe of Gods Ark as they pleaſe, with the excluſion and excommunication of Miniſters, to whoſe cogniſance and juriſdiction ſuch things do moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and immediately appertain, and without whoſe advice it is too often ſent home empty! Again, while the very Kine of <hi>Philiſtines</hi> prefer the honour and home of the Ark of God before their own home and their own Calves, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.12. yet ſome more bruitiſh then the beaſts
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:102981:56"/>of the idolatrous <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> if they and their own iſſue are at eaſe and plenty, care no more then <hi>Gallio,</hi> Acts 18.17. for the honour of the Ark and its Miniſters, ſtill lowing after their own, and not ſtepping one foot to promote the ſecurity, ſubſiſtence and honour of Gods Church.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Grot. de Jure belli l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>ſect.</hi> 10.</note> And further, though theſe <hi>Philiſtines</hi> were grand Malignants to the State of the Jews, yet had they ſome tender bowels of mercy to the College of Prophets in <hi>Gaba,</hi> 1 Sam. 10.5, 10. even as the barbarians had to Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Act. 28.2. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the tenderneſs and indulgence of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Prieſts hath not a bare record, but an <hi>Elogium</hi> and <hi>Encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> from Sacred Writ: <hi>They ſold not their Lands,</hi> even in exigency of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.22. and <hi>v.</hi> 26. <hi>except the Land of the Prieſts only.</hi> How guilty then are all rapacious and rough-handed <hi>Eſaus,</hi> that even in the affluence of peace and plenty have not ſo much as an <hi>Aegyptian</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:102981:56"/>kindneſs for their Prieſts, yea, to whom no <hi>Mummy</hi> is ſo ſweet, ſo nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritive and reſtorative as what is made of the Corps of a bleeding Church! Even he alſo that had an <hi>Ephod</hi> and a <hi>Teraphim,</hi> had a zeale (though not according to knowledg) toward his Prieſt, <hi>Eſto mihi in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotem &amp; patrem,</hi> Judg. 17.10. <hi>Be unto me a Father and a Prieſt.</hi> Though a Father to him in affection and duty, yet was he really <hi>a young man of Bethlehem-Judah,</hi> v. 7. Such reverential reſpect had <hi>Micah</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that young man, as to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But now, God knoweth, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny true Fathers of the Church are made (as we ſay) younger Brothers in the account and eſteem of the World by a ſtrange inverſion and commutation of a blinder zeal then that of <hi>Micah.</hi> Yet once more, the onely Topick by which this <hi>Micah</hi> proveth, concludeth and ratifieth a beniſon to himſelf, is this, <hi>Now I know that the Lord will do me good, ſeeing I have a Levite</hi> (the young Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-<hi>Levite)
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:102981:57"/>to be my Prieſt,</hi> v. 13. His Ethnick Logick had more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and religion in it then any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian that ſeeth no benediction from a ſociety and cohabitation of Prieſts. Thus far Heathen Divinity even in Sacred Writ and Record.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The voice of Heathen for the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> charge and command, that is, Reverence and Maintenance, is ſo Catholick by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct of Nature, as if it had been concluded and enacted by an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Parliament; and this alſo by the grand Sword-men or Grandees of Heathen <hi>Militia.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(a) <hi>X no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon l.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyrus</hi> having collected a grand ſum of money a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Captives, cauſed it to be divided, and gave a Decimation to the Prieſts of <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Diana.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(b) <hi>Plin. l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered the Countries of ſweet O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours and Frankincenſe, ſent a whole Ship-lading thereof to the Prieſts of <hi>Greece,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(c) <hi>Joſeph. Ant.</hi> l. 10. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Nabuch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>noſor</hi> did the like; <hi>Largiſsimum nimis</hi> to the Prieſts of <hi>Belus</hi> Temple.
<note place="margin">(d) <hi>Alex. ab Alex. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> The <hi>Locrians,</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:102981:57"/>in their benevolence to the Clergy, vowed even the ninth part.
<note place="margin">(e) <hi>Caeſar de B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>llo Gal. l.</hi> 6.</note> The cuſtom of the ancient <hi>Gauls,</hi> our own Britiſh Anceſtors, was, to give al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all in effect which they got by War, unto the Gods and their Prieſts.
<note place="margin">(f) <hi>Alex ab Alex. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Lucullus</hi> upon this very account abounded in wealth, becauſe he paid God and his Prieſts ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and abundantly. From the frequent Inductions of pregnant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances I am prone to wiſh that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Engliſh Chriſtians would learn (as <hi>Salomons</hi> Sluggard is bid to do from the Ant or Piſmire, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.6.) even from barbarous Ethnicks and Paynims, what reſpect and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is a due debt to Chriſtian Prieſts and Miniſters. Thoſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh that account the loweſt of the people fit to be Miniſters of God, may learn either from the Heathen <hi>Romulus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(g) <hi>C. Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dig. Antiq. L. l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> who elected Prieſts <hi>genere excellentes &amp; virtute praeſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> that is, <hi>ſuch as were eminent for their ſtock and extraction, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent for vertue;</hi> or from the <hi>Potitii</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:102981:58"/>and <hi>Pinarii,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(h) <hi>Serv. in Aen.</hi> 8.</note> which were two noble Families, and yet were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in ſacrificing morning and evening to <hi>Hercules:</hi> yea, even
<note place="margin">(i) <hi>Plut. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; Oſir p.</hi> 134</note> Kings themſelves were uſually elected either from the Military or Sacerdotal Order; the one, for courage and magnanimity; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for piety and wiſdom. Thoſe Engliſh that account all ſecular char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and encumbrances moſt proper for the backs and purſes of Prieſts, may learn again of the Heathen <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus,</hi> who
<note place="margin">(k) <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſia. Antiq. l.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</note> having conſtituted ſixty publick Prieſts after the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Rome,</hi> granted that they ſhould be <hi>immunes propter aetatem à militia, &amp; propter privilegium exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ab urbanis negotiis,</hi> that is, <hi>free both from military and civil ſervices.</hi> Thoſe that would have them little better then Alms-men or Mendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants, may read a contrary Lecture,
<note place="margin">(l) <hi>Cic.</hi> 2. <hi>de Legib. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſia. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Praeter Idaeae Matris famulos ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis ſtipem cogito;</hi> At <hi>Rome</hi> were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed no Mendicant Prieſts beſides thoſe of the <hi>Idaean</hi> Goddeſs. Thoſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:102981:58"/>that make it a ſport and paſtime to ſee a Prieſt blind or lame, without integrity of his body or perſon, may bluſh to hear <hi>Seneca</hi> ſay,
<note place="margin">(m) <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clam.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos non integri corporis quaſi mali ominis res vocanda.</hi> Any defect or deformity in a Prieſt made him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous in their tender eyes. Thoſe that love to plunder the Eccleſiaſtick Treaſury, and ſo to ſpare their own purſes, have a worſe Divinity then the <hi>Romans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(n) <hi>Liv. l.</hi> 5.</note> who brought much of their own Jewels and Ornaments to the Prieſts of <hi>Apollo</hi> at <hi>Delphos,</hi> having regard rather to publick pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then private commodity. Thoſe that are moſt hungry after ſacred morſels, have more foul ſtomachs and dogged appetites then the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Romans,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(o) <hi>Plin. l.</hi> 18. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> who did not taſte any new Corn or Wine until they had offered their Firſt-fruits to the Prieſts; Juſt as Gods own peculiar people, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.13. Thoſe that look on the whole order and ſociety of them as but unprofitable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of the earth, or as troublers of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:102981:59"/>
                  <hi>Iſrael,</hi> are worſe then thoſe Heathen Cities that gave them reſpects and veneration, as
<note place="margin">(p) Plut. lib. Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoph. cum Principib.</note> 
                  <hi>beneficial to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to their friends, and to the whole Community.</hi> Laſtly, unto all ſacrilegious Malignants to Sacred Perſons or things
<note place="margin">(q) <hi>De Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gib. l.</hi> 10.</note> the Divine <hi>Plato</hi> giveth this moſt Chriſtian Doctrine (as if it came from Saint <hi>Peter</hi> or Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>He is guilty of one of theſe three crimes;</hi> either, firſt, he abſolutely thinketh <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>That there is no God at all;</hi> or, ſecondly, that, if there be a God, he is ſupine, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>is careleſs of Man and his actions;</hi> or, thirdly, that he is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo juſt and terrible to offenders as is pretended, or elſe ſo corrupt that he may be eaſily bribed, or in fine, that he is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a <hi>tame</hi> and <hi>facile</hi> Deity. And
<note place="margin">(r) <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, p.</hi> 84.</note> elſewhere he concludeth peremptorily, that each ſacrilegious man is a dead man, both incurable and incorrigible; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But I hope the vigour and efficacy of ſo many Laws, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchal,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:102981:59"/>Iſraelitical, Evangelical, Engliſh, Eccleſiaſtical, Ethnick, will give life to him that is dead in that treſpaſs and ſin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VIII. <hi>Of the grand Demerits and huge Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies of the Diſciplinarians, or new Clergy: with a Parallel of the New Fanaticks with the Old Phariſees.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe new kind of Clergy, as King <hi>James</hi> entitleth them in
<note place="margin">(a) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> his Inſtruction to Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> have this fair Character from his Royal Pen, <hi>Unruly and fanatick Spirits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Miniſtry, as bad as High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land or Border-thieves for ingratitude, lyes, and vile perjuries.</hi> Their huge enormities are fully and clearly characterized by Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> Arch-Biſhop <hi>Bancroft,</hi> Arch-Biſhop <hi>Whitgift,</hi> Lord Keeper <hi>Puckering,</hi> Doctor <hi>Clerk,</hi> Doctor <hi>Saunderſon,</hi> and others, all fairly and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:102981:60"/>their judgements in
<note place="margin">(b) D. <hi>Tho. Pierce,</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to M. <hi>Baxter,</hi> ch. 5. ſect. 6.—12, 14, &amp;c.</note> a modern Author both ingenious and judicious. But are not all their faults
<note place="margin">(c) Deut. 32.5.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſpots of Sons,</hi> in Scripture phraſe, very ſmall <hi>peccadillos?</hi> In point of contempt and diſobedience to ſupreme Authority, they are Sons of <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Prieſt: In point of contempt of ancient Fathers, they are Sons of <hi>Cham:</hi> In vilifying of the old Prieſts, Sons of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the Son of <hi>Nebat:</hi> In point of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe of the Creed, Sacraments, and reading the pure Word, Sons of <hi>Meſſalian</hi> Hereticks, or Papiſts: In ſacrilege, Sons of old <hi>Eli:</hi> In tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſing, Sons of <hi>Ecebolius,</hi> and the <hi>Priſcillianiſts,</hi> and the like: In co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs, Sons of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> In titles and pretences of ſanctity, Sons of <hi>Gnoſticks, Cathari, Valentinians:</hi> In perjury, Sons of <hi>Zedekiah, the Righteous one of God,</hi> but a perjured ſubject. Theſe, all theſe, are the profeſſed ſubject or Theatre of other Papers of this <hi>Anc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mymus:</hi> and therefore I will not
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:102981:60"/>
                  <hi>actum agere</hi> in this place.</p>
               <p>My preſent Province and Task is, to make an exact Parallel 'twixt the old <hi>Phariſees</hi> and the new <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> and to make it appear that they are both <hi>gemelli fratres,</hi> twin-brothers, in point of opinion and practices, though not contemporary in their births and productions. In purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of which deſign, it muſt be firſt confeſſed, that in both of them there is ſuch variety &amp; contrariety, that it may be ſaid of each Phariſee as the Hiſtorian doth of <hi>C. Caeſar</hi> Son of <hi>Agrippa,</hi> and Nephew of the great <hi>Auguſtus, Tamvariè ſe geſsit, ut nec laudaturum magna, nec vitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraturum mediocr is materia deficiat:</hi> There is a perfect Cheequer-work of matter for ſome ſeeming grand commendation, and for as grand diſcommendation alſo. As there be in the three learned Languages <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba contrariae ſignificationis;</hi> as, <hi>SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CRUM, holy,</hi> and <hi>accurſed,</hi> in the Latine; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the Greek, <hi>affability,</hi> &amp; <hi>ſcurrility</hi> alſo; and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:102981:61"/>
                  <hi>a Saint,</hi> and <hi>a Whore,</hi> in the holy Language: So in theſe two ſorts of perſons, old and modern, if you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare ſemblances and pretences with practices and performances, there is perfect contrariety, contradictions twiſted and accorded together; both are <hi>viri contrariae ſignification is.</hi> Both in their name or titles are <hi>Phariſaei, i. e.</hi> Expounders of the Law of God, from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>expandere, explicare,</hi> that is, Scripture-men, and Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: or elſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>i. e. Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiſts,</hi> by extraordinary ſanctity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove others, <hi>not as other men,</hi> Luk. 18.11. Both Maſters of the Rolls and Records of Heaven, and even <hi>à Conſiliis,</hi> Privy Counſellers, to the King of Kings, yet not loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, or Friends to the Text, though they kiſs the Book. Both in the light and luſtre of knowledge are <hi>Pekochim,</hi> (their own word) <hi>of open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed eyes,</hi> men of new light; One of them forſooth <hi>Or hagnolam,</hi> the light of the firſt magnitude in his age; Another, <hi>Rabbi Hakkodeſh,</hi> the Holy
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:102981:61"/>Teacher: All, <hi>Leaders of the blind,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.19, 20.</note> and have <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a ſlight and ſlender &amp; ſuperficial knowledge in things leſs ſubſtantial and funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental: Yet even both Lights car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in foul and dark Lanthorns: and <hi>the true Light, that enlightneth every one,</hi> diſcovereth their palpable darkneſs, with ſeven or eight <hi>Woes,</hi> Matth. 23.</p>
               <p>Both ſo pure and defecate that they will not <hi>eat with Publicans and ſinners,</hi> Matth. 9.11. nor ſuffer a <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> once <hi>to touch</hi> Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.39. Theſe cannot digeſt even the Lords Supper, nor have Communion with ſinners and ſcandalous perſons, but have faſted ſeven or ten years upon the ſame account and ſcore. Their word is, <hi>Touch me not: for I am ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier then thou,</hi> Iſa. 65.5. and Chriſts own word alſo, <hi>Nolite tangere fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum Phariſaeorum,</hi> Luk. 12.1. <hi>Firſt of all, beware ye of the leaven of the Phariſees.</hi> Both their Faſts alſo were with ſowre, leavened,
<note place="margin">Matth. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured</hi> and <hi>exterminated countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:102981:62"/>yet in their very Faſts they had good ſtomachs <hi>to devour widows,</hi> Gods houſe, and his Prophets. Both have <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">Acts 16.5.</note> 
                  <hi>the moſt ſtrict and accurate way and walking;</hi> all walking <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>circumſpectly,</hi> in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. They alway ſay, <hi>I go, Sir,</hi> and go not, as the ſmooth and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Son, the Type of the Phariſee of old, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.30. Laſtly, will the Reader exhauſt and ſwallow down their prime and accumulative excellencies by whole-ſale, as they ſay? How are both affected to Gods day? No ears of Corn to be pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the hungry, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.1. nor a blind man to be cured, on that day, <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.16. How affected to Gods Cauſe, or Gods Corban? Why? <hi>Calcab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> patrem:</hi> Father and Mother and all natural relations ſhall be laid aſide, or overlaid by the weight of their affection to the Cauſe of God or <hi>Corban,</hi> Matth. 5.5. How affected and inclined to Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? Praying oft, and long, and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. How in Conference?
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:102981:62"/>
                  <hi>Ye, being evil, ſpeak good things,</hi> Matth. 12.34. Such ſacred Texts as theſe, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.19. <hi>I will eſpouſe thee to my ſelf in righteouſneſs;</hi> Joel 2.28. <hi>Your ſons and your daughters ſhall propheſie, — your young; men ſhall ſee viſions;</hi> and Mal. 4.3. <hi>Ye ſhall tread down the wicked, for they ſhall be aſhes under the ſoles of your feet:</hi> Theſe, all theſe, they eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and monopolized to their own ſanctified ſelves. They, the onely Saints to be ſaved; all others, caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awayes: as Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> on Mal. 4.3. <hi>En &amp; ecce tunicam Patris veſtri, ô Fanatici!</hi> Behold, the full and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect livery and cogniſances of the very Fathers of our modern Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees and Fanaticks! Thus old and new Phariſees and Fanaticks, like ſpiritual Fidlers in Religion, do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume and wear the livery and badge of ſome Noble-man, that they may not appear to be what they are known to be by the Statutes of God and the Land. They are like ſome Medals in the world, which on the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:102981:63"/>one ſide have <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>pourtraicture of an Angel,</hi> or of a Saint, and on the other ſide the image of an infernal Fiend or Spirit. The Reader ſhall preſently under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that they both are <hi>viri contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae ſignificationis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is it now poſſible for ſuch and ſuch qualified perſons, in ſeven or eight gallant particulars, to be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of diſobedience and open hoſtility and rebellion againſt their Kings, Gods Lieutenants? Let <hi>Joſephus,</hi> himſelf a Phariſee, give in evidence and remonſtrance againſt his own Fraternity:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Antiq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 13 <hi>c.</hi> 18.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, in our Engliſh Tranſlation and practice alſo, <hi>The Phariſees were of ſuch prevalence with the people or vulgar, that if they ſpake againſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther King or Arch-Prieſt, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently obtained the Publick faith and commen credulity.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 23.</note> Yea, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>if, being envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and malicious, they ſpake never ſo
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:102981:63"/>malignantly,</hi> they could gratifie and pleaſure their friends, and injure their foes. Such hath been the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and impoſture of our modern Fanaticks, by oſtentations and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments of pretended Piety, both in reference to the beſt King and beſt Prieſts. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſuch potent and prevalent Factors and Agitators a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Kings, that they beat out and exiled <hi>Alexander</hi> their King out of the coaſts and confines of <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Gilead,</hi> as <hi>Sigonius</hi> telleth us. Yea,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Republ. Hebraeor. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> they made ſo ſtrong infuſions of principles of diſobedience and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in their Proſelytes, that <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eri etiam tormentorum patientiâ ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctateres obſtupefacerent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> very Boyes were ſo obſtinate Martyrs, even in rebellion and ſufferance, that they did amaze and ſtupifie the honeſt Spectators. And ſuch Monſters have been among modern Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is it poſſible, again, for ſuch and ſuch qualified perſons to be
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:102981:64"/>guilty of Violence and Extortion? The word of our great Maſter is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.39. Very <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyes</hi> for violence, though very Saints in ſemblance and pretences. Both have <hi>devoured Widows houſes,</hi> Gods houſe, and the Prieſts, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>long prayers,</hi> and their <hi>ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at gnats.</hi> They <hi>kill, and whip, and perſecute Prophets from city to ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Mat.</hi> 23.34. While both of them ſeem <hi>by violence to take the Kingdom of heaven,</hi> and they forſooth, <hi>the vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ones,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to take it by force;</hi> yet both of them are, I fear, Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>violent Extortioners,</hi> that <hi>ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi> They are very fortunate ſons of violence, if they have <hi>Gods Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeed</hi> in each ſort of violence, to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth alſo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Is it poſſible for thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, thoſe <hi>accurate and exquiſite walkers to the extremities</hi> of Gods commands, (as the word importeth) to be guilty of <hi>Covetouſneſs, which is Idolatry?</hi> When our Saviour ſpake of <hi>not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:102981:64"/>God and Mammon, Luke</hi> 16.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. theſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate walkers <hi>ſnuffed at</hi> it, made mouthes and jeers and mimical ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures; and that upon that very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that he talked of Charity, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality and Almes, <hi>ver.</hi> 10, 11, 12. Though Piety ſeemeth to fill their ſails, when <hi>they compaſs ſea and land to gain Proſelytes,</hi> yet Profit and Mammon is the perpetual compaſs by which both ſteer their courſe. Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Phariſees have thruſt their ſequeſtred Brethren out of houſe and home, without the aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo much allowance as eje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Monks and Nuns had.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exam. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. p.</hi> 110, 111.</note> Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Weſton</hi> Lord Prior of the Order of St. <hi>John</hi> had a yearly penſion of a thouſand pounds; <hi>Rawſon</hi> the Sub-Prior, of a thouſand Marks; ſome of the Brethren, of two hundred pounds <hi>per annum;</hi> and thirty pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> he that had leaſt. And this may ſerve for an Uſe of Inſtruction, or of Reproof and Reprehenſion, of our grand Idolatrous Fanaticks,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:102981:65"/>which were more ready <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to jeer and mock,</hi> their grave, godly and learned Predeceſſors, then to pay them a fifth, yea a tenth, or twelfth part.</p>
               <p n="4">4. May we not alſo arraign and endict them as guilty of Pride, high ſpiritual Pride?
<note place="margin">Joh 7.49.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Rabble and Herd of unſanctified <hi>people, that know not the Law,</hi> were <hi>accurſed</hi> by the ſowre and ſwelling and leave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Teachers. <hi>Populus terrae, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcatio pedum Phariſaeorum;</hi> The Heads of the people, if not of their own <hi>Godly party,</hi> were but competent Foot-ſtools for the ſacred feet of the new Teachers.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Take now a Breviary of their accumulative Impieties and Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Their worſt, and yet natural, face is ſeen in one cryſtal glaſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.23. They <hi>omit</hi> and neglect, as unneceſſary and ſuperfluous duties of Saintſhip, <hi>judgment,</hi> (it is lawful for ſuch <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to ſpoil ſuch <hi>Aegyptians) and mercy,</hi> (Charity and Good works belong to the Court of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:102981:65"/>
                  <hi>Rome,</hi> in their own words) <hi>and faith,</hi> that is, fidelity and veracity in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, Covenants, Oaths. Thoſe of Allegeance and Supremacy have been like Almanacks out of date for many years together; or like Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> duſt, ſwept up and laid together behind the doors of our <hi>Phariſees hypocrits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. There is a concurrence and conjunction of them in one point, which is the higheſt aggravation of all their Crimes and Demerits: The old Phariſee doth thus dogmatize like a Stoick,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſeph. Ant q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 18 <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>Vide plurae apud D. Pierce,</hi> Of Divine Philan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thropie, <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3, 4.</note> 
                  <hi>All deputed and linked to Fate and God.</hi> Our own Phariſees alſo ſay, <hi>Reprobates are compellea with a neceſsity of ſinning,</hi> and <hi>ſo compelled that they cannot chuſe but ſin.</hi> Yea, a grand Doctor in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the very Blaſphemies of that F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, ſaith, <hi>They intended no more then what by multitude of Scriptures they were led unto, E.R.</hi> pag. 60. and further, <hi>Sin by God is abſolutely wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, becauſe ordainable to his glory,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:102981:66"/>E. R.</hi> pag. 101. To which I return either a better Doctor,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tak. in Cam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ian. p.</hi> 115.</note> 
                  <hi>Dignus eſt quem Deus ſtatim fulmine ad imum inferorum barathrum dejiciat;</hi> or a better Author then both, <hi>Deus non volens iniquitatem, Pſal.</hi> 5.4.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Laſtly, our Phariſees do love <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Whileſt <hi>Presbytery,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>ſect. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>like a young heir, thinketh the Father hath lived long enough, and being impatient not to be in the Biſhops chair and authority, all art is uſed to ſink Epiſcopacy, and lanch Presbytery in England.</hi> And while they <hi>garniſh the ſepulchres</hi> of their Fathers, ſuch as Biſhop <hi>Cranmer, Ridley, Jewel, &amp;c.</hi> they <hi>perſecute</hi> the ſurvivers <hi>from city to city.</hi> Adde again their <hi>ſwallowing down the Camel</hi>-ſins of Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, and Perjury, and Oppreſſion, and Sacrilege, &amp;c. and yet <hi>ſtraining</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd <hi>at the gnats,</hi> a Surplice, a Ring, a C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, or a May-pole.</p>
               <p>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, if the Phariſees rightly held a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>Tranſmigration of ſouls</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> did, then the ſouls of the Phariſees have had a
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:102981:66"/>Tranſmigration, and poſſeſs the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fanaticks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>sect. IX. <hi>A Second Parallel, of the New Clergy with the old Primitive Fanaticks.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS the true Goſpel-Chriſtian is deſcribed or defined in holy Writ, to be one <hi>ſealed with the Spirit of Chriſt, Eph.</hi> 1.13. and to <hi>have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived grace for grace, John</hi> 1.16. that is, Figure for figure, Linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for lineaments, and Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for impreſſion; and <hi>the new man created after God in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe, Epheſ.</hi> 4.24. So all Pſeudo-Chriſtians of this later Age are ſealed with the ſpirit of Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Fanaticks. They in the firſt Age were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>paterns and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plars;</hi> and theſe in our Age and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration are their exact <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Both have the ſame lineaments and figures: Not <hi>Ovum ovo ſimilius.</hi> The image in the glaſs doth not
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:102981:67"/>more lively expreſs the natural face and feature, then the reflexion of modern Teachers doth reſemble and repreſent the firſt <hi>Ideas</hi> and exemplars of primitive Pſeudochri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Fanaticks.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In point of affectation and oſtentation of huge Purity and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity above their Brethren. Thoſe of the Order of <hi>Zelotes</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a little before its deſtruction by the <hi>Romans</hi> (a ſad <hi>omen</hi> in our dayes) called and accounted themſelves <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the onely <hi>zelous</hi> Brethren <hi>of good and godly enterpriſes</hi> and deſigns for the power of Godlineſs.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſeph. de Bello Jud. l.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 87<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> And others they deemed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, l.</hi> 5. <hi>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>as a very herd of unſanctified creatures.</hi> This is the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the firſt Seal. In our Age the <hi>New Clergy</hi> (as King <hi>James</hi> calleth them) have arrogated and appropriated to themſelves a very ſpiritual Monopoly of Zele, <hi>i.e.</hi> the onely <hi>pure, precious, zelous, Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Teachers, and Godly party.</hi> The Diſciplinarian Zelote is onely for
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:102981:67"/>
                  <hi>the Throne of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>the Sceptre of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>the Government of Chriſt.</hi> All others are <hi>Barbarians, without and without,</hi> (as the word importeth) even without the pale of the Church, without the Sceptre and Throne of Chriſt. How many alſo have we of <hi>Baſilides,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiph. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> 4. <hi>de Baſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>de.</hi>
                  </note> the old Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, his Order and <hi>Claſsis!</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>We, we onely, the Men; and all other, Degs or Swine,</hi> for carnal or ſpiritual impurity, in their eyes. Laſtly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiph. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>r.</hi> 70. <hi>p.</hi> 827.</note> how many <hi>Audians,</hi> old Hereticks, in our new Age, that had <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>very admirable and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful converſation and deportment</hi> in ſome ſingularities of Zele; and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they would not uſe the ſame Common Prayers with any others of a different perſuaſion from themſelves! Thus in the firſt point, of Affectation and Oſtentation of Purity, the old and new Fanaticks are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the laſt being formed and created <hi>ad imaginem &amp; ſimilitudinem</hi> of thoſe their Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſts
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:102981:68"/>in Doctrine and Purity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The next figure and impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the former Seal is in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and Diſobedience to Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick Parents and Governors. Even a ſober and ingenuous Reader of ſome paſſages of the holy Father St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> would almoſt believe him a ſon and Writer of the preſent Age; He doth ſeem to give ſo plain a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative and hiſtory of the occurrences of the modern Age.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyprian. Epiſt.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 29.</note> 
                  <hi>Aliqui de Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris nec Evangelii, nec loci ſui memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> Some John Presbyters, being forgetful of the Goſpel, and alſo of their own place and ſtation, <hi>neque nunc ſibi praepoſitum Epiſcopum cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantes, — cum contumelia &amp; contemtu praepoſiti totum ſibi vendicant,</hi> with contempt and contumely of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop do aſſume and arrogate all to their own Presbyterian hands, not at all reſerving <hi>Epiſcopo honorem cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drae;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſt.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> whilſt in the pure Antiquity, long before St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Idem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>epiſt</hi> 27. <hi>p.</hi> 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Inde per temporum &amp; ſucceſsionum vices, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcoporum ordinatio &amp; Eccleſiae ratio
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:102981:68"/>decurrit, ut Eccleſia ſuper Epiſcopos conſtituatur, &amp; omnis actus Eccleſiae per eoſdem praepoſitos gubernetur:</hi> In all Ages and <hi>ſeries</hi> of ſucceſſions each Act, Canon or Order of the Church was ruled and managed by the hands Epiſcopal. And again,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Idem, epiſt.</hi> 69. <hi>p.</hi> 208.</note> 
                  <hi>Inde ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata &amp; haereſes obortae ſunt &amp; oriun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, dum Epiſcopus, qui unus eſt, &amp; Eccleſiae praeeſt, ſuperbâ quorundam praeſumtione contemnitur.</hi> It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> by our practice, <hi>Thence Schiſms and hereſies ariſe, whileſt ſuch Governours are contemned by the proud preſumtion of ſuch Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks.</hi> Such a forward and early Fanatick was <hi>Aerius,</hi> who, miſſing a Biſhoprick himſelf, made this popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Doctrine, <hi>Nullâ differentiâ diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni:</hi> Whoſe Phantaſme was at once convicted by St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in <hi>Africa, Epiphanius</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Philaſtrius</hi> in <hi>Europe.</hi> Such afterward were thoſe fond and fooliſh Presbyters,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Carthag.</hi> 3. <hi>can.</hi> 42.</note> 
                  <hi>Pler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſtolidi adverſus Epiſcopos ſuos cervices erigunt Presbyteri, vel conviviis ſibi conciliantes plebem, vel certè perſuaſu
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:102981:69"/>maligno &amp; illicito, &amp;c.</hi> Thoſe <hi>fooliſh</hi> Smectymnwans <hi>did either careſs the vulgar by treatments, or by unlawful and malignant perſuaſions.</hi> Yet worſe and more impudent Fanaticks were they that did in ſome meaſure ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a Biſhop,
<note place="margin">Ignot. Ep. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>did all things,</hi> or any thing, <hi>without his direction</hi> or influence; and ſo were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry contemtuous and ironical</hi> Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Of the ſame Paſte were the ſowre and leavened Donatiſts, who in a ſport or May game <hi>Canina cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora membris Epiſcopalibus conjunxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>contra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>armen.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ſic ſaltare fecerunt,</hi> conjoyned and coupled in a loud Sarcaſm the bodies of dead dogs with the living members of the ſacred Angels of the Church, and ſo made them dance in a poſture, for the recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of vulgar eyes. The like ſad ſport did the Heathen uſe to <hi>George</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. they tyed him to a Camel, and then drew him off again, and burnt the beaſt and the Biſhop in the ſame
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:102981:69"/>flames. Our modern <hi>Smectymnwan</hi> Proſelytes were ſurely the jocular and merry ſons of ſuch or ſuch Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Another Image and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription is in reference to Supreme Parents, the <hi>Abimelechs,</hi> as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Philiſtines</hi> called their Kings. In this point <hi>Judas Galilaeus</hi> was one of the firſt and grand Fanaticks. The cauſe or occaſion of his Sedition is thus repreſented by the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ub. Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cit.</hi> 2. <hi>in Raron. ſect.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Non eſſe decorum aut aequum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Regem, &amp;c.</hi> That it was not comely nor equitable to impoſe any other King over men, beſide God himſelf the King of Kings. And he quoted the Sacred Text to warrant his profane and ſeditious Poſition, <hi>Deum tuum timebis, &amp; illi ſoli ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies;</hi> whileſt the truth is, they <hi>made God to ſerve by their ſins,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 43.24.</note> as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaith, and his word to ſerve their pride and ambition. For God expreſly commandeth their ſervice and obedience even to Pagan and Idolatrous Governors, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 27.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:102981:70"/>&amp; 40.9. And <hi>Zedekiah</hi> was puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for his diſobedience to <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar, Jer.</hi> 24. Sure I am, all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> and Eccleſiaſtick deſpiſers of Kingly dominion, have more ſignal and ſingular Obligations then any other Nation or Kingdom under the Sun.
<note place="margin">Spelm. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Praeſat.</note> For in <hi>England</hi> was the firſt Chriſtian King, <hi>Lucius;</hi> and the firſt Chriſtian Emperour, <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> and the firſt Chriſtian Queen, <hi>Hele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na;</hi> and no leſs then twelve Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kings martyred by the bloudy hands of Infidels: And there have been more pious Kings in <hi>England</hi> then have been in any other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, though never ſo ſpacious and populous. Let even a Fanatick be judge, whether any Antiquary can ſhew Record or Regiſter of the like ſpecialties of the Divine favour to any other Kingdom under the Sun. No Nation can more juſtly chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the Prophets word,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 49.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Reges nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tritti, Reginae nutrices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Another Parallel and reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance is in diſobedience to catholick
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:102981:70"/>thers of the Church. Such a Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick was <hi>Abailardus</hi> in Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nards</hi> dayes, whoſe Motto and By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word was, <hi>Omnes Patres ſic, Ego non ſic:</hi> If all the Fathers ſaid, <hi>Yea, Abai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lardus</hi> ſaid, <hi>Nay.</hi> And none ſuch Saints as the Antipodes to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Yet higher, in Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> early dayes, <hi>Cùm vos veritas urget, Patres dicitis erraſſe. — ſed Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbia vos ligavit in cathedra peſtilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae.</hi> To old Donatiſts (and new Fanaticks) all the Fathers were wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Stars, and erroneous; and their own pride made them fixt, and firm in the chair of Scorners, or of Peſtilence. How many Echoes of <hi>Abailardus</hi> and the Donatiſts have we heard in this empty, windy and hollow age of Fanaticks! Who may juſtly expect that their ſucceſſors and poſterity ſhould in reaſon and religion repay and return their diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience <hi>lege talionis</hi> upon their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers heads and humours. This was the artifice and impoſture of <hi>Julians</hi> mind:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>crat. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:102981:71"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>All his Predeceſſors he ſcornfully load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with bitter jeers and taunts. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius,</hi> of the ſame temper, would not vouchſafe to learn <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c</hi> 32.</note> 
                  <hi>the Books of the Ancients,</hi> becauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſwollen big with conceit of his own elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>he deemed and accounted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a better man,</hi> a better Father, <hi>then any of his Ancients.</hi> In the preſent point either <hi>Abailardus,</hi> or the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> or <hi>Julian,</hi> or <hi>Neſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> were the Types; and our Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, the Anti-Types.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Another ſeal and impreſſion is in point of diſaffection and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Natural Parents. <hi>Nova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> that had ſo much affectation of purity in himſelf, had bitter diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and diſreputation of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents:
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Vita <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>i.</note> 
                  <hi>Spoliati ab illo pupilli, fraudatae viduae, pecuniae quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Eccl. denegatae; pater etiam ejus in vico fame mortuus, &amp; ab eo nec ſepultus:</hi> He at once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauded and oppreſſed the Widow,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:102981:71"/>plundered the Fatherleſs, ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly robbed the Church; and when his own Father died &amp; periſhed with Famine in the ſtreet, his zeal could not afford him Chriſtian bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial. A barbariſm condemned by a whole Council of Heathen Authors. For the <hi>Greeks</hi> call Funeral Rites <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Latines, Juſta:</hi> And he that omitted them (as <hi>Novatus</hi> did) was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>an accurſed, devoted fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,</hi> or <hi>Anathema.</hi> Such an unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſon was to be ſerved with a Writ <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and, if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed, he was excommunicated all ſociety, both Sacred and Civil, and to be fined beſides. Yet how many Fanaticks in caſe of Gods <hi>Corban,</hi> or Gods Cauſe, have with Phariſees renounced, and with <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatus</hi> abdicated their own natural Parents, of their Country, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily alſo, and almoſt all natural Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations! And ſome Fanatick zele of modern Diſciplinarians dareth make it a Canon and Conſtitution,
<note place="margin">1 Book of Diſcipline 9. Head.</note> 
                  <hi>That if the Parents gain ſay marriage
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:102981:72"/>upon the common g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ounds, of want of gudes, or diſparity of birth, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter may</hi> (non obſtante parente) <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to marriage. For the work of the Lord ought not to be hindred by the corrupt affections of men.</hi> So the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplinarian Doctors.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Thoſe that thus vilifie the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and Regal Authority &amp; Unction, by a parity of Reaſon and Religion alſo do vilifie or nullifie the Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotal Unction or Authority. Theſe delight to ſee the holy Ark placed upon a Cart, and Chriſt upon an Aſs and upon a Colt the Fole of an Aſs, and <hi>Jeremy</hi> the high Prophet in a Dungeon, and the ſacred Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery upon ſordid, Lay and Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beian heads and hands. Thoſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks muſt aſſume old <hi>Iſchyras</hi> (the grand enemy of the holy Biſhop <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius</hi>) as the Protoplaſt of this errour and phanſie; whoſe ignorance and impudence did ſo far ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize him in his own phanſie, that, being a Lay-perſon,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>he did arrogate the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:102981:72"/>name of Presbyter to himſelf,</hi> as many late Fanaticks have done. Which phanſie and impudence the grave Chriſtian Hiſtorian calleth expreſly <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a matter demeriting more then a ſingle death.</hi> Such intruding <hi>Uzzahs, Korahs,</hi> and <hi>Sauls</hi> do as much demerit death it ſelf under the Goſpel, by the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſentence of the judicious Hiſtorian, as thoſe others did by the expreſs verdict given under the Law. Or if ſuch Fanaticks will not own their Father <hi>Iſchyras,</hi> they may aſſume another, <hi>Zacchaeus,</hi> for their reverend Progenitor: of whom an ancient Father informeth us,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiph. l.</hi> 3.</note> that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>he out of a bold and impudent attempt did invade the holy Prieſthood;</hi> and others with him, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>by impulſe of dreams</hi> and inſpirations, did as our Fanaticks do, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>adventure upon the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Biſhop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Both primitive and preſent
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:102981:73"/>Fanaticks have another fair (or rather foul) reſemblance and correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to each other, and that is in their ſtrange, uncouth &amp; affected po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures and geſtures in prayer. Such haters of Images of all ſorts, that (as the Phariſees before them both) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">Mat 6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>they deface</hi> Gods own Image <hi>in their own Faces;</hi> as if their <hi>leaven of Hypocriſie</hi> (as Chriſt calleth it) muſt needs ſowre and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figure their very countenances and aſpects.
<note place="margin">Luk. 12.1.</note>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theod de Oracul.</hi> l. 10.</note> Such were thoſe devout Orators, that did all <hi>in ſacris cum tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batione &amp; cervicis jactatu,</hi> with hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and pitiful agitations and toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of eyes and heads. Such were thoſe which <hi>Dio Chryſoſtomus</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth,
<note place="margin">Caſaub. Ex r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Orat.</hi> 1. <hi>de Regno,</hi> that did <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, had ſtrong commotions and a kind of torvity and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſeverity in their looks. Such alſo were the old Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiph. Haer.</hi> 48. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Taſcodrugitae</hi> or <hi>Paxillonaſones,</hi> which had a ſtrange trick <hi>of laying their
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:102981:73"/>Fore-finger upon their noſe in prayer,</hi> and all <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to ſhew ſome ſtrange <hi>dejection and diſcountenance,</hi> and as a piece of ſad and rigorous <hi>will worſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Our new Fanaticks have made another exact Parallel, with the old Fanatick <hi>Meſſalians,</hi> by a ſtrange conjunction and commixture of plain contraries. Both grand Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to the Holy Spirit; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>They called their very dreams new Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies.</hi> Both did phanſie the Holy Spirit, and did <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>gave ſenſible and viſible evidence of his preſence</hi> in them. Both were enemies to the conſtituted Diſcipline and Faſts of the Church. Yet both thoſe highly Spiritual perſons ſo far from <hi>drinking into one Spirit,</hi> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.) in the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Euchariſt, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theod. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>they ſaid the Divine food did neither help nor hurt</hi> the ſanctity of their ſpirits. Our
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:102981:74"/>own <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fanaticks, by a conſtant and continued abſtinence from the Divine Sacrament for eight or ten years together in their Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, have unhallowed the Sacrament, vilified the Spirit, unchurched them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Congregations, and made the wild <hi>Meſſalians</hi>-their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in impiety. And while the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Text ſaith,
<note place="margin">Joh. 6.56, 58.</note> 
                  <hi>He that cateth my fleſh, and drinketh my bloud, ſhall live for ever;</hi> theſe Fanaticks were <hi>even dead while they lived,</hi> as that Father and Church-Hiſtorian concludeth them.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Our Fanaticks and the old Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts are clearly <hi>fratres gemelli,</hi> Twin-brethren, in much impiety and iniquity. Both arrogate to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Optat. Milev. l.</hi> 2. <hi>init. p.</hi> 34</note> 
                  <hi>ſpecialem ſanctitatem de ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia,</hi> ſome ſingular and ſpecial ſanctity from their ſpiritual pride.
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 3</note> 
                  <hi>Nolunt ſe dici fratres noſtros,</hi> ſaith the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Father; They ſcorned to call others <hi>Brethren,</hi> which were not of their Godly party.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 27 <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 81.</note> How ſtood they affected to Kings? <hi>Quid Imperatori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:102981:74"/>cum Eccleſia?</hi> What have Kings to do with Church-affairs? was their ordinary mode of ſpeech. How to Churches and Altars?
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 53. <hi>Altaria frangere, radere, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movere.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tegulis pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi cruentati, duo occiſi:</hi> With the very tiles and utenſils of the Church they killed ſome upon the Altar, and wounded others. How to the bleſſed Euchariſt?
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 116.</note> They caſt it to the very dogs; which, <hi>non ſine ſigno Divini ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicii,</hi> turned, and rent and tore <hi>domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos, tanquam ignotos &amp; inimicos,</hi> their very maſters, as if ſtrangers and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to them. How diſpoſed to the orthodox Biſhops? <hi>Deuterium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 72</note> 
                  <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenium, Getulicum, Dei Epiſcopos, lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guae gladio jugulaſtis, fundentes ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, non corporis, ſed honoris:</hi> Their tongues were ſharp ſwords to wound them, and to ſhed the bloud, if not of their bodies, yet of their honours. How called they their prime Leaders and Circumcellions?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 106.</note> 
                  <hi>Agoniſticos Sanctorum duces,</hi> the prime Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders and Captains of Saints, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth; and yet ſuch <hi>Boutefeus</hi> of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick injuſtice and violence, <hi>ut nullus
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:102981:75"/>creditor eo tempore exigendi habuit li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertatem:</hi> They put ſuch a bar to all judicial proceedings, that the Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour could exact nothing for any debts, for fear of the <hi>Sanctorum Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> Laſtly, how malicious in their lies and accuſations? They ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout many Pamphlets and Paſquils, <hi>mittentes ubi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 23.</note> 
                  <hi>litteras livore dictante conſcriptas, ut rumoribus falſis cuncto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum auribus mendacia inſererent:</hi> By falſe news and rumours they planted and ſowed lies in all ears. They were alſo <hi>in caedibus immanes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 53.</note> 
                  <hi>filios pacis ad bella provocantes,</hi> moſt bloudy and cruel to all oppoſits, and ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking ſons of Peace to <hi>Mars</hi> his field.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Our new Fanaticks, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever edition, perſuaſion or denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, are twin-brethren with the old <hi>Eunomians. Eunomius</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sozom. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 26.</note> ſomewhat eloquent in his Schiſm, very contentious, and a Maſter of Logick-diſputes and Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſmes. The Fanatick Proſelytes
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:102981:75"/>to this Doctour of Arianiſme, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they gave little or no commendation or <hi>Encomium</hi> to Integrity of life, or Morality, Mercy or Charity, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>if men entertained not the ſame opinion with themſelves.</hi> But <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. All that they attended to and commended, was, if one were hugely contentious and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigious for their opinions, and could conquer by diſputes. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. He was <hi>of the Godly party</hi> that would and could mainta n their eſpouſed Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Tenents. Such godly and pious Opiniatouts were the Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, as <hi>Ignatius</hi> repreſenteth and characterizeth them: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>They had no regard of charity, no care of the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, the orphan, the oppreſſed, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned,</hi> but whether rigid, ſevere and diſputing Gnoſticks. That our
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:102981:76"/>
                  <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fanaticks have inherited this vertue of their Fathers, <hi>Eunomius</hi> and the Gnoſticks, I dare atteſt the perſonal experience of above thirty years paſt. They have ever neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected Integrity, Morality, Charity and Mercy to all diſſenters from them; and their Charity hath been very cold to Widows, Orphans, and impriſoned perſons: And the higheſt vertue of the Godly party hath been to diſpute and diſcourſe of their own opinions touching Kings, Biſhops, Common-prayer, Ceremonies, &amp;c. and he that doth this, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is <hi>the Godly man,</hi> and of the Godly party, whether he be Presbyterian, or Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, or of what other opinion and perſuaſion ſoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:102981:76"/>
               <head>SECT. X. <hi>A third Parallel, of Fanaticks with Papiſts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is a kind of Miracle, and very worthy of obſervation, That in many things there is an unhappy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incidence even of extremes, which ſeem to ſtand at the vaſteſt diſtance and contrariety. In things natural, extreme cold parcheth the graſs,
<q>—<hi>Borcae penetrabile frigus adurat,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Virg Geor.</note>
                  </q> as well as extremity of heat. In Mathematicks, lines drawn from the oppoſit points of the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference meet in the Centre. In matters Moral, the Prodigal, that utterly diſclaimeth and forſweareth Covetouſneſs, yet pulleth upon himſelf by his waſtefulneſs a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of being covetous and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſive. Thus, thus in matters of Religion alſo, the extreme and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit Parties to Orthodox Religion
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:102981:77"/>have a coincidence and conjunction of opinions, <hi>non obſtante</hi> their ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming contrariety and contradiction to each other.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is a curſed poſition which both concentre in, notwithſtanding their diſagreement otherwiſe, That lawful Soveraigns may be reſiſted by their Subjects, and Arms of hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty taken up in the cauſe of Religion; not the weapons of the firſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Prayers and Tears, but the arms of the Fleſh, Fire and Sword. This point of Popery, never heard of in the firſt ten Centuries, is ſtrongly aſſerted by modern Doctors. For their grand Obſervator with all the Diſciples of this ſanguinary Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine do in aſſerting their Tenents onely tranſlate <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and the Popiſh Writers into Engliſh. And this Cholerick Doctrine was not kindled and inflamed in the World till <hi>Ioh. de Pariſiis,</hi> and <hi>Iac. Almain,</hi> as the learned Biſhop of <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe</hi> in his <hi>Sacroſancta Regum Majeſtas,</hi> pag. 14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Both agree in unchriſtian par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:102981:77"/>contrary to the ſolemn charge and obteſtation of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to Biſhop <hi>Timothy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim 5.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>I charge thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and the elect Angels, that thou—do nothing by partiality.</hi> Their impaling of the Church to their own party, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding all others from hope of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, is infallibly the grand Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality. Thus the <hi>Pontificii</hi> make the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Catholick Church</hi> conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible terms, and make ſubjection to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> a neceſſary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite of a Chriſtian Church; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it a formal difference in the very definition of the Church, <hi>Sub regimine unius in terris Vicarii, Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Pontificis,</hi> that is, <hi>which is under the government of the only Vicar of Chriſt on earth, the Biſhop of Rome.</hi> As the old Donatiſts confined the limits of the Church, <hi>in angulo &amp; particula Africae,</hi> in a corner and ſmall part of <hi>Africk;</hi> So do our new Engliſh ones, either to their Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, Congregate, or Presbyterial Claſſes. Theſe only, the <hi>Godly,</hi> the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:102981:78"/>
                  <hi>Brethren,</hi> the <hi>Pretious,</hi> the <hi>Children of God;</hi> all other, <hi>vile, unſavoury ſalt, Barbarians.</hi> This is contrary to the temper of thoſe ancient and godly ſouls:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; Auguſt. Epiſt.</hi> 203.</note> 
                  <hi>Velint, nolint, fratres ſunt,</hi> ſaith charitable <hi>Optatus.</hi> Will they, or nill they, he would ſtyle them <hi>Brethren.</hi> So <hi>Greg. Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zene, Orat.</hi> 33. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I call you Brethren, though ye uſe unbrotherly dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings with us.</hi> Bleſſed is that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which doth <hi>religare,</hi> bind and tie us in bonds of obedience to the Head, and in charity to the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, though unworthy Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the obligation of Oaths and Covenants. The Romaniſts hold that their Lateran <hi>Iupiter,</hi> the Pope, hath a power paramount over the conſciences of men, that he can ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Subjects from their Oaths and Allegeance to their Prince, that he can reſcind, relax, and oblige again, and even <hi>contra jus naturale diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> diſpenſe with the breach of the Laws of Nature, in this caſe. As for
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:102981:78"/>our modern Theologues, it is the complaint of the Reverend Prelate, <hi>Utinam nonnulli qui rectiſsimè dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, non peſsimè imitarentur:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Saunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, de Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramento.</note> What they moſt juſtly condemn, they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly practice themſelves: For <hi>illi de facto exercent quod Papa de jure ſibi vendicat,</hi> they practice what the Pope ſaith he may do. It is moſt certain that all Papal or Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an diſpenſation can be but <hi>res fori ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terni:</hi> but the obligation of an Oath is <hi>intus in foro conſcientiae,</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the inward man. Therefore <hi>ſententia prolata à Judice in foro non ſuo, eſt de jure nulla,</hi> i. e. <hi>The ſentence of a Iudge in a Court not of his juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction is vain and invalid.</hi> Let them teach us who can give a diſpenſation from that Oath wherein all ſwear, <hi>No power on earth can abſolve them.</hi> Thus like <hi>Samſons</hi> Foxes they are joyned in the tails;
<note place="margin">Iſa. 9.15.</note> 
                  <hi>And the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet that teacheth lyes, he is the tail,</hi> ſaith the Royal Prophet. And they have their firebrands alſo, by which they diſſolve the bonds of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:102981:79"/>Oaths, and ſet every Community, yea the whole world, in combuſtion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In exalting themſelves <hi>above all that is called God,</hi> i. e. the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate. Thus <hi>T. C. pag.</hi> 144. <hi>ſect.</hi> 1. <hi>Chriſtian Princes muſt remember to ſubject themſelves to the Church, to ſubmit their Scepters, to throw down their Crowns before the Church, yea, to lick the duſt of the feet of the Church.</hi> So the Reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Bramhall,</hi> in his <hi>Warning piece,</hi> giveth us account of the ſame Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and conformable practice of the Scotiſh Presbytery. And is not this the ſame Divinity that <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> preached to <hi>Frederick Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſſa?</hi> on whoſe neck while he ſet his feet, he did quote Scripture for his pride, <hi>Super aſpidem &amp; baſiliſcum ambulabis, &amp; conculcabis leonem &amp; draconem.</hi> This pride the Church of <hi>England,</hi> together with the whole ancient Church, doth deteſt. <hi>Artic.</hi> 37.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat.</hi> 12. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.</note>—<hi>The chief government of all Eſtates, even Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, doth appertain, &amp;c.</hi> and, <hi>All ſorts of
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:102981:79"/>Spiritualty and Temporalty ow next to God a natural obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. In that unquiet principle, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minium fundatur in gratia.</hi> For <hi>Aquinas, Cajetane, Bellarmine,</hi> and <hi>Suarez, &amp;c.</hi> hold that any Prince who falleth from the Romiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, maketh a forfeiture of his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and may be deprived of his hereditary rights. The contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the Covenant among us did publiſh no different Doctrine from this. For he that ſweareth to defend his Prince with this limitation, <hi>in the defence and preſervation of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion,</hi> will ſuppoſe himſelf juſtly excuſed, if he do not defend him in caſe of his deſertion or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from the ſame Religion. For it is the rule of Reaſon, <hi>Exceptio in caſibus non exceptis firmat regulam in oppoſitum.</hi> And whileſt it is ſtill pleaded, even to this day, that <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Presbytery never diſſolved Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> (as <hi>Iohn Corbet;</hi>) ſure to place the Supreme power, or Co-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate, (as he ſtill maintaineth) in
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:102981:80"/>Lords and Commons, the power of chuſing great Officers and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of State, the power of the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi> and government of all Forts, to ſhare the Kings Revenues, to plunder and kill fellow-ſubjects, look altogether like ſome ſuch thing in <hi>Presbyters</hi> as <hi>diſſolving of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Both guilty of Sacrilege in alienating the Communion, in part, or in whole, from Lay-hands; and both upon the ſame reaſons and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretences, of high reverence to the ſacred Myſteries. <hi>Propter pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculum effuſionis Sanguinis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Liranus,</hi> and others, on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>for fear of ſpilling</hi> (in the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick or Natural ſenſe) <hi>the blood of Christ.</hi> And, <hi>Irreverentia &amp; profana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones Sacramenti vix evitari poſſent in tanta multitudine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Euchariſt. c.</hi> 28. <hi>n fine.</hi>
                  </note> ſaith <hi>Bellarmine; becauſe irreverence and profanations cannot be avoided in ſuch a multitude.</hi> Are not the fears of <hi>ſpilling</hi> the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and <hi>profaning</hi> the body of our Lord, the very ſame pretences
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:102981:80"/>of debarring ſo many ſouls from the ſacred Myſteries?</p>
               <p n="7">7. In point of reading the pure Word of God. The pure Popiſh poſition is this, in their own words,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pract. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olog. tract.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 27. <hi>concl.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Salubriter Laicos à lectione Scriptura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum arceri, &amp; ſufficere ut ex praeſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Paſtorum &amp; Doctorum Eccleſiae vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta curſum moderentur,</hi> as <hi>I. Molanus:</hi> This Jewel is not to be caſt before Swine, but the people are to live by the dictates or ſermonizings of their Paſtors and Teachers, and, as little Infants and Babes, battle only by chewed meat from their Nurſes mouthes; as they illuſtrate their ſacrilegious intentions. Our Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Teachers, that in practice could hardly vouchſafe the people the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a Pſalm or Chapter, and were wholly for their own long Prayers and longer Sermons, did practically at leaſt concentre ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Papiſts, or elſe with the Anabaptiſts,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hooker,</hi> Eccleſiaſt. Polity.</note> that called the writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten word <hi>a dead letter</hi> (as I have heard the Word called without a
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:102981:81"/>Sermon) and the Bible, <hi>Babel,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs quickned and edified by their Expoſitions and Sermons. It is <hi>T. C.</hi> his poſition, <hi>It is untrue, that ſimple Reading is neceſſary in the Church: A number of Churches have no ſuch order of ſimple reading.</hi> Thus the grand Patriarch, <hi>T. Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. In caſe of Vows &amp; Covenants. I will not magiſterially and dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically conclude and determine, but may piouſly and compaſſionately fear, that they are guilty of the three Popiſh Vows. When they Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted to <hi>aſsiſt with their Eſtates and Fortunes</hi> in the Godly Cauſe, and that without conſent of their Parent (which Vow the Father might cancel by Gods Law, <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.) is not this Covenant near a-kin to the <hi>votum Paupertatis?</hi> When they covenanted, <hi>None ſhall ſuffer himſelf, directly, or indirectly, by any combination, perſuaſion or terror, to be divided, &amp;c.</hi> Who, I pray, can totally hinder all arguments from
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:102981:81"/>all impreſſions? Is not this a-kin to <hi>votum Continentiae,</hi> the vow of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency, which none can intallibly promiſe to himſelf? When, laſtly, there have been multitudes of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, Covenants, Negative Oaths, and Engagements, were not theſe very like <hi>votum Obedientiae,</hi> the vow of Obedience, to their <hi>General</hi> alſo, as the Papiſts call him in Religious Orders.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Jeſuitical Doctrine of Probability is this,
<note place="margin">Myſtery of Jeſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, <hi>Praeſ. &amp; pag</hi> 95, 96.</note> 
                  <hi>Quamvis ipſe Doctor ejuſmodi ſententiam ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivè falſam eſſe certò ſibi perſuadeat,</hi> Though he hold it certainly falſe, yet from the judgement of one or two grave Authors he may recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend what is moſt acceptable to the Queſtioniſt, <hi>ſi haec illi favorabilior &amp; exoptatior ſit.</hi> In the Divinity of our Fanaticks, a <hi>Calvin</hi> in <hi>Geneva,</hi> a <hi>Knox</hi> or <hi>Buchanan</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;c. ſhall preponderate the moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Doctrines of the Catholick Church, and all Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. The Doctrine of Direction of
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:102981:82"/>intentions,
<note place="margin">Pag. 123, 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> (as in a Duel, not to the ſin of Revenge, but to our profit and advantage, the ſaving of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, &amp;c.) maketh guiltleſs with the Jeſuite: The very Fanaticks grand plea for popular Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Inſurrection and Hoſtility. Let the Reader peruſe <hi>The Myſtery of Jeſuitiſme:</hi> it is <hi>Mysterium Fanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The grand controverſie of late hath been wholly managed by the force of unwritten Traditions, or blind Fundamentals. Ask the new Teachers, by what Law of God, or Law of <hi>England,</hi> may ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects take up Arms againſt Kings, and againſt Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.2</note> 
                  <hi>He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth, ſhall receive to himſelf damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> Why, it is an unwritten Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, no Law of God or the Land. Where have they liberty reſerved to reſume and revoke the Supreme Power into their own hands? It is an unwritten Tradition. In what caſe of Law may they take Forts, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies, Magazines, and all the <hi>Militia?</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:102981:82"/>All theſe are begged only as blind and unwritten Fundamentals: No authentick Law for their tradition or reception.</p>
               <p n="11">11. There are many Characters of Antichriſt common to both.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummat. mundi. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Chriſti</hi> 220.</note> 
                  <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polytus,</hi> an ancient Writer, near 1400. years ſince, gives theſe ſhrewd indications; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Houſes of God ſhall be uſed as Cottages, Liturgy ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, ſinging of Pſalms ſhall ceaſe, reading of Scriptures ſhall not be heard.</hi> Not one ſyllable of this but hath been verified of late, as a learned Miniſter and eye-witneſs of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions of the Welſh Churches doth teſtifie.
<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Nicol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
                  </note> Not three Sermons in all <hi>Monmouth-ſhire,</hi> and others, even on the Lords day; the Sacraments prohibited; Liturgy, Singing, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wholly neglected. Sure not the Biſhops foot, but the foot of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt hath trodden upon our Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Teachers heads, and hearts alſo.</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:102981:83"/>
               <p n="12">12. Laſtly, though both have their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.18</note> 
                  <hi>ſpeak great ſwelling words</hi> of their own fixedneſs and immobility in their reſpective Religions and Profeſſions, yet have they been <hi>Reeds</hi> ſufficiently <hi>ſhaken with the winds of Doctrine.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.14. <hi>L'Eſtrange</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>John Corbet,</hi> p. 184.</note> In Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths days,</hi> of 9400. Parochial Prieſts there were not above 80. Rectours of Churches which conſtantly and invincibly refuſed the Oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy. And though
<note n="*" place="margin">Mr <hi>John Corbet.</hi>
                  </note> a grand Presbyterian telleth us in print, <hi>they are all fixed and reſolute, not like to be reduced to the practice of former times;</hi> and, <hi>This intereſt is not like a Meteor, which vaniſheth away, but of a firm and ſolid conſiſtence, like a fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Conſtellation,</hi> pag. 43.— <hi>never will be extinguiſhed while the ſtate of England continueth Proteſtant,</hi> pag. 44.
<note place="margin">Arch-B. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſwood</hi> Hiſt. p. 479.</note> Yet, after the Conference at <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> 1603. of 9000 and more Parochial Miniſters only 49. ſtood out, and were depoſed for diſconformity: Whileſt the late odious and deſpicable Clergy, for
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:102981:83"/>obedience to their Mother the Church, and loyalty to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and piety to their Oaths and Obligations, have this fair <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and indication of their conſtancy,
<note place="margin">Hiſt. of Engliſh and Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byt. p 316</note> that <hi>of</hi> 97. <hi>Miniſters within the walls of London</hi> 85. <hi>were driven from their Churches: not to mention many thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſands that never bowed their knees to</hi> Baal-berith, <hi>from our</hi> Dan <hi>to our</hi> Beer-ſheba.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XI. <hi>A Fourth Parallel, of modern Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks with the Pagan</hi> Myſtae <hi>or Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. IN the Roman Republick there was a grand Controverſie tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Tribune-Magiſtrates &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the <hi>Ediles</hi> &amp; <hi>Judices Decemvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</hi> The caſe clearly this; the Tribunes were <hi>ſacroſancti</hi> and immoveable, becauſe they had <hi>legem ſacratam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. de jure B. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9. <hi>ſect.</hi> 9.</note> both Law and Oath, for their eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment and ſettlement; the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemviri</hi>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:102981:84"/>and others had onely <hi>lege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſimplicem,</hi> a Law only, but not any interpoſition of a ſolemn and nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Oath. The Tribunes were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>v. l.</hi> 3.</note> becauſe <hi>Tribunes relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> publica populi Romani tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>atur:</hi> the intervention of an Oath, in which their Religion was concerned, made them immutable and permanent; The other were revocable and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by ſome new Edict and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the Roman Senate. And <hi>Tib. Gracchus</hi> was condemned for his wilful abrogation of <hi>Octavius</hi> from his Tribuneſhip. In our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh State there hath lately been the very ſelf-ſame caſe or publick controverſie. The Lords poſſibly, Spiritual and Temporal, were as the <hi>Decemviri</hi> and <hi>Aediles</hi> among the Romans: They had <hi>legem ſimplicem,</hi> no interpoſition of a ſacred and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h; and were upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court not ſo wholly immovable and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Fanaticks and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ew that our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and Governour had
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:102981:84"/>
                  <hi>legem ſacratam</hi> for a ſufficient defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſative againſt injurious hands, a double Oath, of Allegeance and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy; beſide a third, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural <hi>Obedience, which all ſorts, of Spiritualty and Temporalty, did bear to him next to God,</hi> according to the words of the Statute 12 <hi>H.</hi> 8. The Roman Pagans were far better Chriſtians then any of our Fanaticks, of what denomination or perſwaſion ſoever. They kept their Oath <hi>though to their own hindrance</hi> (as they might imagine;)
<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.4.</note> and our Engliſh Fanaticks thruſt out <hi>legem ſacratam cum juramento. Cùm tota religio po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli Anglicani tucbatur,</hi> When the whole Religion of our Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was concerned, the triple cord, of Supremacy, of Allegeance, and of Nature, was ſnapped aſunder by theſe violent <hi>Samſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Even among Pagans the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of Blood-Royal was ſo horrid and execrable, that <hi>caedes Principis, quantumvis hoſtis, non impunita,</hi> the Blood of a King, though a profeſſed
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:102981:85"/>perſonal enemy, never found Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or an Act of Indemnity among them. As <hi>David,</hi> in Sacred Writ, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the murder of his Royal ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my (even <hi>Saul</hi> the ſon of <hi>Cuſh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 7. Tit.</note> an Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopian, from the blackneſs &amp; foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his diſpoſition) with the death of the Executioner, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. So the Pagan <hi>Auguſtus</hi> was highly vindicative againſt the murderers of <hi>Caeſar;</hi> and <hi>Severus</hi> likewiſe, againſt thoſe of <hi>Pertinax;</hi> which Act alone (as <hi>Herodian</hi> writeth) procured him <hi>incredibilem gloriam &amp; regnandi ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem,</hi> both incredible honour and much ſecurity. The Pagan <hi>Vitellius</hi> likewiſe ſeverely revenged the death of <hi>Galba,</hi> his profeſſed enemy. Yea, <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> for crucifying the King of the Jews, our Lord &amp; Maſter, met with juſt revenge, and loſt his head, by the piety even of <hi>Nero,</hi> as <hi>Sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> telleth us. Yet in the blood-ſhot eyes of all our modern Fanaticks I fear that neither the Cannon at <hi>Edge-Hill,</hi> nor the Ax in another place, ever yet appeared ſo horrid
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:102981:85"/>and execrable as thoſe other inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of villany did in the eyes of <hi>David,</hi> or <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> or <hi>Severus,</hi> or <hi>Vitellius,</hi> or <hi>Nero.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The devotion of the Pagans was very eminent and exemplary. They brought many Donatives and Honoraries to the Temples of their Gods out of the ſpoils and plunder of their enemies; Which by the <hi>Greeks</hi> were called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by the <hi>Latines manubiae.</hi> Such were thoſe that were ſent to <hi>Apollo</hi> at <hi>Delphos, Herod. l.</hi> 8. and thoſe which the <hi>Athenians</hi> gave to <hi>Minerva. Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Tarquinius Superbus de ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nubiis captarum urbium templum ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xit.</hi> Our Fanatick Teachers cannot vie one ſuch act of zele as theſe. It ſhall be more tolerable therefore for ſuch Pagans at the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then for ſuch Chriſtians. Among Gods people there was a double Exchequer, one Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, the other Civil, <hi>Fiſcus regius;</hi> as appeareth <hi>Joſh.</hi> 6.19. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 7.51. The Temple of <hi>Saturn</hi> had a
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:102981:86"/>Treaſury <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> had his ſacred Exchequer, <hi>Appian. de Bello civ. l.</hi> 5. In <hi>Greece</hi> they had a ſacred Council for ſuch a Treaſury, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Strab. l.</hi> 9. But in our worſe then Pagan dayes, what Widow, what Souldier hath caſt in two Mites almoſt for twenty yeares paſt?</p>
               <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Herodot.</hi> &amp; <hi>Diodor. Sic. apud Gregor. Tholoſ. de Repub. l.</hi> 26 <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>ſect.</hi> 16.</note> An <hi>Aegyptian</hi> King was ſo unmoveable in his integrity and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, that (like <hi>Pharaoh</hi> before him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.22, 26.) he preferred the intereſt and welfare of the Prieſts before his own. For a <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane</hi> God having often moleſted his ſleep with horrid dreams, and told him that his Empire could not long be proſperous, <hi>felix &amp; di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>turnum,</hi> unleſſe he would lay violent hands upon his Prieſts; at laſt he ſent for them, and having acquainted them with his dreams, told them plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Malle ſe purum omnique ſcelere ſolutum ab Aegypti regno abſtinere, &amp;c.</hi> That he had rather part with
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:102981:86"/>the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Crown and Sceptre, then be an actor in ſo execrable a Tragedy. Our Fanatick <hi>Myſtae,</hi> without being moved and frighted by dreams and viſions, have plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſequeſtred many Prieſts, and taken from them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>all their Livings,</hi> as the Phyſicians did from the poor wretch in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. And whereas the Pagan King would rather quit his Crown then injure the Prieſts, theſe have ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their very life-bloud; and yet, though they have ſwallowed the beſt Livings, they are as lean as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> raſcall Kine were after they had eaten up the fat ones.
<note place="margin">Hiſt. of <hi>Engliſh</hi> &amp; <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Presb. 234</note> In our grand Metropolis, of 97. Miniſters within the walls no fewer then 85. (as hath before been ſaid) were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoiled of their Free-holds by the violence of Fanatick Presbyterians; and 115. in the Suburbs and Pariſhes adjoyning; beſides thoſe of <hi>Pauls</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The Pagans were ever very firm to and tenacious of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:102981:87"/>Oaths and Engagements. <hi>Pacta ſcripto ſancita violare nè abje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſsimo quidem homini decorum eſſe arbitror:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Clapm. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 8</note> It is unhandſome for the moſt abject perſon living to violate his engagements,
<note place="margin">Plutarch. Qu. Grac.</note> ſaith <hi>Belliſarius.</hi> The <hi>Megarenſes</hi> and <hi>Corinthians,</hi> when ſome would forfeit their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>role, and not return money accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to promiſe for their liberty and redemption, <hi>Fidem fallentes tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam ingratos &amp; injuſtos notabant:</hi> Their very friends became their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and ſet a Mulct upon them as ungrateful and perfidious. When the <hi>Romans</hi> were requeſted by the <hi>Campanians</hi> to afford them Auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaries againſt the <hi>Samnites</hi> their Confederates, they returned them this reſolute anſwer,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Clapm. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſp.</hi> 2. <hi>ſect.</hi> 67.</note> 
                  <hi>Arma, Deos prius quàm homines violatura, adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Samnites vobis negamus,</hi> Such Arms as muſt firſt fight againſt the Gods, by fighting againſt our Faith and our Aſſociates, we wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny you: as <hi>Livie.</hi> The moſt gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Character of a Souldier in the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:102981:87"/>fury and rage of war is thus made even by a Pagan Poet,
<q>
                     <l>—<hi>Optimus ille</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Sil. Ital.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Militiae, cui primum poſtremum<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> tueri</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Inter bella fidem.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> Our modern Fanaticks, though they brag that <hi>ſince the times have been upon their Tropicks, they have been leaſt Tropical,</hi> yet how ſlippery, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious and temporizing they have been, I leave to a far better Pen and Pencil: Perfidious to Articles,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Th. Pierce</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Barlee, c.</hi> 4. <hi>ſect.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 12.</note> to their Ordinaries, and to the <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premus Ordinarius totius Angliae.</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>—<hi>Pudet haec opprobria vobis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potuiſſe refelli.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> For modeſties ſake I forbear any new Century of their ſcandalous Crimes.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Amongſt the Pagans, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <hi>Myſtae,</hi> Flamins and Officers in Divine things were not required or permitted to ſwear at all, out of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:102981:88"/>their devout and reverential reſpects both to Prieſts and Oaths. The judicious Hiſtorian giveth this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plutarch. Qu. Rom. Qu.</hi> 28.</note> Either becauſe an Oath is <hi>tormentum liberorum,</hi> and therefore incongruous for ſo free and ingenuous an Office as the Prieſt-hood; Or elſe, <hi>quia non convenit de rebus parvis non ei fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem habere cui ſacrae &amp; manimae creditae,</hi> it was judged moſt impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, not to give credence to the Prieſt in ſmall and civil occurrences, when Divine and Sacred matters were committed to his charge and fidelity; Or becauſe execrations, which are ſtill annexed to Oaths, are illegal and improper for a Prieſts mouth;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Idem, Qu.</hi> 44. <hi>p.</hi> 470.</note> Or laſtly, becauſe <hi>publicum periculum, ſi perjurus ſacris operetur;</hi> there might fall publick vengeance on all if the Prieſt were perjured. And it is an honour to that ſtout Champion <hi>Hercules,</hi> that <hi>non niſi ſemel duntaxat juravit,</hi> he never ſwore but once. Our Fanatick Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers have not been ſo nice, tender
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:102981:88"/>and ſcrupulous as the very Pagan Prieſts and Flamins. For how many of them have ſix or ſeven times, in the Univerſities, at Ordinations, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions, &amp;c. took the Nationall Oaths, and yet after all have ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Proteſtations, Covenants, Negative Oaths, and Engagements? not ſo abſtemious, not ſo full of fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, as <hi>Hercules</hi> and the Roman Flamines. Sure they are <hi>leves &amp; nauci,</hi> i. e. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, according to old <hi>Varro's</hi> derivation, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 2 Cor. 1.18, 19. Whereas the Romans had one Temple conſecrated to the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs <hi>Fides,</hi> I fear few of our Engliſh Fanatick Teachers would make competent Prieſts and Officers in that Temple.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <note place="margin">Philo. Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus. Plutar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus. Iſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates in Panathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naico.</note> The Pagans had a moſt affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionate and conſtant gratitude to their Kings and Prieſts. Our Lord and Maſter ſeemeth to commend them for ſtyling them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.25. That honourable Title was given to the Roman Emperors.
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:102981:89"/>For the <hi>Pontifices;</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Cic. in Orat. pro domo ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ad Pontiſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Omnis Reip. dignitas, omnium civium ſalus, vita, libertas, arae, foci, fortunae, domicilia, veſtrae ſapientiae, fidei poteſtatique commiſſa &amp; credita eſſe videantur,</hi> All the dignity, all the ſecurity of all ſubjects, yea their lives, houſes and goods, were committed to the Prieſts, as the beſt Guardians and Patrons of all. Our Fanatick Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers were never yet guilty of that publick and univerſal gratitude to Prince or Prieſt. King <hi>James</hi> (as above ſaid) calleth them <hi>High-landers and Border-thieves, for lyes, perjuries and ingratitude.</hi> For their conſtant murmuring and ingratitude to our <hi>Moſes</hi> and our <hi>Aarons,</hi> they have <hi>Judaicum opprobrium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. <hi>Bernard. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rm.</hi> 11. <hi>in Cant.</hi>
                  </note> as the Holy Father calleth it, the very <hi>ſtigma</hi> of the Jewiſh Nation; who made no leſs then ten mutinies and inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections againſt the meekeſt and yet the ſtouteſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> and againſt <hi>Aaron</hi> the Saint of the Lord, thrice for Water, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.24. &amp; 17.2. <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.2. thrice for Bread,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:102981:89"/>
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.2. <hi>Num.</hi> 11.4. &amp; 21.5. twice about the way, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.1. &amp; 21.4. and twice againſt the Prieſt, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.11. — 41. The Fanaticks in all ages have had more of the Jewiſh murmuring againſt Governors, then of the Pagan grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to Benefactors.</p>
               <p n="8">8. The prudent Pagans were of ſuch integrity to the publick Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and concernments of State, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical and Civil, that they ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred and abjured all ſcurrilous and ſeditious Pamphlets and Paſquils of Innovators. <hi>Plato</hi> maketh this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non or Maxime, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 7 <hi>De Legib.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>It was not permitted or tolerated to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate phanſies to publiſh any writing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were tranſmitted to and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Judges and Lawyers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">D. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ert. in Prota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gora.</note> When <hi>Protagoras</hi> had divulged ſome impious Tenets and Opinions, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:102981:90"/>
                  <hi>The Athenians burnt his Books in the Market-place, having by a publick Cryer collected all the Copies.</hi> And <hi>Valerius</hi> telleth us,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>V. Max. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>ſect.</hi> 12.</note> that <hi>L. Petilius Prator ex authoritate Senatus igne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto in conſpectu populi cremavit,</hi> by the authority of the Senate burnt certain dangerous Books before the eyes of the people. But our fiery Fanaticks have neither the ſpirit of moderation, nor of prudence, nor of ſubmiſſive obedience, as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Plato,</hi> and others. <hi>Diſputare malunt omnes quam vivere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1.</note> as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith. The Pamphlets (divulged in ſpite of the Statute 23 <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 3. and others of later date) of Mr. <hi>John Corbet, Douglas,</hi> &amp;c. are more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>ut in ignem mittantur quam ut in lucem emittantur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could eaſily multiply theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallels, if I did not ſpare my Reader and my ſelf. He that vieweth the actions of both impartially, will be ready to think, that though it be a curſe in the Goſpel touching ſome Chriſtians,
<note place="margin">Math. 18.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Sit tibi tanquam Ethni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:102981:90"/>yet it may look like a bleſſing for ſome wild Chriſtians, if they were in many points of Morality even <hi>tanquam Ethnici.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have impartially repreſented the <hi>Genius</hi> and Character both of the Old and of the New ſort of our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Clergy: And I cannot eaſily ſuſpect but that thy own determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and concluſion will be that in the Goſpel touching Old Wine and New, <hi>The Old is better.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 5.39.</note> If thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt Religion and Learning, Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Charity, Reaſon and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Honeſty, thou wilt not be ſo far impoſed upon, as to impoſe the right hand of favour and fellowſhip upon the younger Brother, as once he did, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.14. Or if thou doſt thus impoſe thy hands, thou art likely to ſay as the Biſhop <hi>Marcianus</hi> did after he had ordained one <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batius,</hi>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:102981:91"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Better to lay hands upon Thorns or Brambles</hi> then upon thoſe who of late would have had the Bramble reign over all the Cedars in State and Church alſo. And few or none even of their Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical and Cardinal Leaders but have crimes, and not only <hi>ſpots of Sons,</hi> Deut. 32.5.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sozom. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 14.</note> I have read a ſtory of one <hi>Pachomius</hi> a devout Abbot, who having under him four and twenty ſorts of Monks, according to the number and nature of the Letters of the Greek Alphabet, pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thoſe that were ſimple, plain and upright, in the Letter <hi>Iota,</hi> which conſiſteth <hi>unâ lineolâ rectâ,</hi> of one ſtraight and ſmall line; but ſuch as were of a more involved and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed <hi>genius,</hi> and full of <hi>anfractus,</hi> he ſet under Z ζ <hi>Zeta,</hi> or Ξ ξ <hi>Xi,</hi> by reaſon of the various winding and turning of thoſe Letters. I know many, and I heartily wiſh even all, Old Engliſh Clergy juſtly placed (as <hi>Pachomius</hi> his honeſt Monks)
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:102981:91"/>under the Greek <hi>Iota.</hi> But I much fear another ſort, which have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding much of the winding, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and involved nature of the Letter ξ <hi>Xi.</hi> To all the people of our Engliſh Church I wiſh the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Malachi's</hi> benediction, that <hi>God would open unto them the windows of Heaven,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mal. 3.10.</note> 
                  <hi>and pour them out a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, that there may not be room e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to receive it.</hi> To all true hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Miniſters I wiſh the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah's</hi> benediction,
<note place="margin">Jer. 31.14.</note> that <hi>God would ſatiate their ſouls with fatneſs. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:102981:92"/>
            <head>Syllabus Sectionum.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. SEction Introductorie, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning modern</hi> Zamzum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mims, <hi>and miſchievous A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs against the Clergy.</hi> p. 1</item>
               <item>II. <hi>Of the grand Merit of the Old Engliſh Clergy.</hi> p. 8</item>
               <item>III. <hi>Of the old Engliſh Law, and Courteſie to the Clergy.</hi> p. 21</item>
               <item>IV. <hi>Of the Moſaical and Iſraelitiſh account.</hi> p. 33</item>
               <item>V. <hi>Of the Evangelical account, or under the Goſpel.</hi> p. 46</item>
               <item>VI. <hi>Of the Eccleſiaſtick or Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive account.</hi> p. 66</item>
               <item>VII. <hi>Of the Natural Account,</hi> i. e. <hi>Patriarchal, and Ethnick.</hi> p. 73</item>
               <item>VIII. <hi>Of the grand Demerits and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies of the new Clergy. A Parallel of our new Fanaticks with the old Phariſees.</hi> p. 85</item>
               <item>IX. <hi>A ſecond Parallel, of our Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Teachers with old Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Fanaticks, in ten Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</hi> p. 99</item>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:102981:92"/>
               <item>X. <hi>A Third Parallel of our Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Teachers with Papiſts, in twelve particulars.</hi> p. 119</item>
               <item>XI. <hi>A Fourth Parallel, of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick Teachers with the Pagan</hi> Myſtae <hi>or Doctors.</hi> p. 133</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Concluſion.</hi> p. 147</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
